Hi, my name is Chad and this is your
zero to hero Kubernetes fundamentals
course. Now, as your instructor, you
should know I am CKA and CKAD certified.
I've also been an education specialist
for 20 years, which means that I have
spent the majority of that time in
actual classrooms with actual students,
not just from talking behind a camera.
which means the content of this video
has been tested, bloodied, and proven to
work for many folks that are looking to
get started in Kubernetes. So, the plan
in this video is that we are going to be
going through all of the fundamentals of
Kubernetes, everything that you need as
a foundation to pass your CCAD or your
CKA exam, or if you're just looking to
get proficient with Kubernetes in
general. Now, batter up, cuz here's the
pitch. This video is a great starting
point, but if you are looking for
hands-on labs, AI support, human support
from folks like me, then get yourself
over to Alta3 Academy, where we offer
full courses, which will cover
everything you need to know about
Kubernetes, including mock exams and
everything that's needed for the CKA and
the CKD exams. That link is inside of
the description, and I would love to see
you there. Here is a list of all the
content that we're going to be talking
about inside of this video. If you are
already somewhat proficient with
Kubernetes, use the timestamps in the
description to be able to hop to
whatever it is that you need to learn.
However, if you are new to Kubernetes, I
strongly suggest that you just go
through the content in the order that it
is presented. You ready to rock? Let's
get started. To begin, before we start
getting into the what is Kubernetes and
the how do I use Kubernetes, let's talk
about the why even use Kubernetes.
Kubernetes is all about enabling a
certain sort of lifestyle in application
deployment. Consider this that
ultimately it comes down to we've got
some code along with dependencies that
are needed in order for that code and
its application to run. in a style of
application deployment known as
microservices. That typically means,
hey, let's put all of that code and its
dependencies inside of an isolated
environment called a container. Now,
that comes with a whole bunch of
advantages. It's really easy to spin up
containers, and if you have any
experience with Docker, that's great. If
you don't, that's not a problem at all.
It's really easy to replace containers,
which means that if you need to update
or make changes to these applications,
that can be done in a snap. And then
there's the whole joke, oh, it worked on
my computer, then we'll ship your
computer. That whole joke is pretty
accurate into what containers do. That
if you create it so it works inside of
one container, then it should work when
you deploy it elsewhere. And a big big
part about what's cool about containers
is that they are scalable. You can
create as many different copies of them
as you want. Thing about containers is
they are not meant to hang around
forever. Whether they die because you
tear them down or because something
happens to them. I mean, that's sort of
an inevitability. And while there
certainly are manual ways to deal with
things like that, here's where we start
getting into some more problems when it
comes to container management in the
traditional sense without Kubernetes.
So a container in order for it to work
has to run on top of an existing
environment. So let's say a virtual
machine. And you can create as many
containers inside of this virtual
machine as you want so long as resources
permit. But eventually you're going to
get to the point where oh I don't have
any more room for containers. Your
virtual machine is tapped. But you need
more. You still need to scale out. Well,
let's talk about how that could lead to
a couple of different disaster
scenarios. Scenario number one, your
host machine runs out of resources. You
don't have any more room for containers
and as a result, containers may like not
be able to expand. Issue number two,
containers die and they get ignored.
There are ways for you to work around
this, but you have to work fairly hard.
And spoiler alert, this is something
that Kubernetes can handle for us. And
the third scenario is is that all these
containers are running on the same
virtual machine, right? So if your
virtual machine dies,
no, all those containers just went down
with it and there's nothing that's set
up in order to bring those back.
Fortunately, Kubernetes has an answer.
Here's where we might be taking your
prior knowledge about Docker and
applying it to how it works inside of
Kubernetes. Containers and Kubernetes
work exactly the same way they always
did, whether they're being created by
Docker or something else. But Kubernetes
containers are placed inside of
Kubernetes objects called pods. Pods are
really just wrappers that are being
placed around containers. Kubernetes
manages pods, not containers. So by
putting them together as one unit, it
makes it easier to control. So that
package deal, that pod and container
still needs to live on top of some
environment. The container needs to draw
its resources like we saw before.
Traditionally, that can be on a virtual
machine. In a Kubernetes environment,
when you add virtual machines to it,
those are called nodes. And you can add
multiple nodes to the same
environment. When you do that, you wind
up literally exponentially increasing
the total amount of resources that might
be used for lots of pods. And when you
combine all of those nodes together, you
get what are called a cluster. Now,
there are two flavors of nodes. The ones
in green on my screen right here, these
would be our worker nodes. And this is
where you would expect to see the vast
majority of pods, which remember are
wrappers around containers to be
created. And as you can see, there can
be more than one pod on like a given
node. There can be uh a disproportionate
number of pods on these different nodes.
Some of these nodes may be in different
sizes, like the one on the right is
smaller, therefore maybe it can only fit
one pod. Whereas the one on the left is
bigger and that one can hold three. A
cluster is just an aggregate of
resources. Now the other type of node
which is again also a virtual machine is
known as the controller. The controller
does exactly what it sounds like. It is
the hub of all of the tools that are
required in order to keep your cluster
running. And we're going to talk more
about those later. As a general rule,
you don't want to be just willy-nilly
putting pods on top of the controller
node. Why? Well, because the controller
node's busy. It needs its resources to,
you know, manage the cluster, which is
pretty important. Now, before we get to
the fun stuff and before we actually
start building pods and things like
that, it is important to have an
understanding of what is going on under
the hood. what's ticking and running
inside of these nodes and what tools are
we using in order to access and
interface with our Kubernetes cluster.
The first tool that we need to learn and
one of the many things that starts with
the word cube because Kubernetes just
loves putting cube in front of
everything is cube control. And cube
control is the CLI tool that is going to
be installed inside of your personal
workstation, your laptop, wherever it is
that you're working from. That is where
cube control is installed. And what that
enables you to do is that from your
machine, you are able to access the
cluster. Note that we're doing so by con
connecting to the controller node that
we spoke of earlier and that all cube
control requests are going to be
received by the API server. So all
communication inside of Kubernetes is
done through an API which if you know
about API APIs and HTTP and all that
stuff great. If not, it's not a deal
breakaker, but we'll talk about why
that's going to be relevant later. Now,
in order for cube control to talk to a
given cluster, after all, what's
stopping somebody from installing cube
control and talking to any cluster in
the world is that it must be configured
to do so. So, if we take a look, what
you see here in miniature is a cube
config file. This is a document that
should be on the same machine where cube
control is installed and it includes
such things as like the location of the
cluster, but also includes where is the
certificate and key file again located
on your personal environment that will
allow you to authenticate who you are
and talk to that cluster. Without that
setup, cube control is never going to
work. But moving on through the anatomy
here, talking a little bit more about
the API server. Like I said, all
communication like all action that
occurs inside of a cluster is done
through an API, which means that a
request is sent to the API server. it
decides whether or not that request is
valid and then as a response will take
certain action or return certain
information depending on what it is that
you're trying to do. So the API server
is what will be returning information to
you here at cube control. It is what
also reaches out and communicates to
every single node that are part of our
cluster. Remember, you can have multiple
nodes, multiple virtual machines, all
part of the same cluster. The API server
is also the only thing that talks to
ETSD, which is what we'll talk about
next. All right, we're here on the
official Etsy website, which means that
this is definitely third-party and it's
not just something that got invented by
Kubernetes. CD was around long before
Kubernetes was. And what is CD? It is a
strongly consistent distributed key
value store that provides a reliable way
to store data that needs accessed by a
distributed system or a cluster of
machines. Well, you just described the
cluster there, right? Distributed system
of cluster of machines. So, stores
state. It's all about storing data. So,
specifically when it comes to
Kubernetes, where is it being written?
How many nodes are attached to a
cluster? Where is it written how many
pods are running? And are they actually
running? Are they erroring out? Like
where is it written that whether or not
pods are able to talk to each other and
things like that. Just Etsy did. And as
a result, CD is something that as either
an administrator or as a developer when
it comes to Kubernetes, you should be
very respectful of it because losing is
like labbotomizing your cluster. You are
going to lose all track of all things
that are running inside of it. Another
component that is part of the controller
is theuler. And what this is doing is
that
it's put this pod up on this node right
here. No. Okay. Like Tetris
theme. What happens to pods is that they
get put on nodes, right? Well, what
makes that decision? Sure, we can make
that decision ourselves, but as a
result, we want Kubernetes to decide
that. So the scheduler is what's going
to try to make sure that you've got like
an equal distribution across your nodes
for the most part plus obeying any sort
of rules that get put in place either by
you or by the system itself just to make
sure that everything is following the
rules. Speaking of following the rules,
there is the controller manager. You
might picture the controller manager as
like the sheriff. I'm here to make sure
all you piled stay in line. I'm here to
kick butt and chew bubble gum. And I'm
all out of bubble gum. The controller
manager actually manages a lot of
different dammons that control a lot of
the behaviors of how your cluster runs.
Now, if you're brand new to Kubernetes,
these may not mean a whole lot to you
right now. But for instance, objects in
Kubernetes are tracked via namespaces
that they can be controlled through
role-based access control which are
connected to service accounts that
you'll be creating copies of pods called
replicas. That's something that needs to
be tracked as well. And the controller
manager is what's in charge of all of
that. Now, Cublet, Cublet is present on
every single node inside of your
cluster. And regardless of what this
diagram might be showing you, Cublet is
also present on top of the controller
nodes as well. But Cublet is kind of
like the eyes and the ears of every node
inside of your cluster. It's responsible
for all sorts of things. making sure
that the containers are started, stopped
or restarted appropriately on each node
in your cluster. Any instruction that
comes from the controller node is going
to be received by Cublet. So suffice it
to say, if Cublet encounters problems on
one of your nodes, well then your node
is now in trouble because that is your
sole connection to the rest of the
cluster. And now what about Docker? A
lot of people say, "Well, should I be
using Docker or should I be using
Kubernetes? And if not Docker, some
other container runtime engine." Here's
the thing. It's not either or. If you're
using Kubernetes, you are using Docker
or containerd or whatever. Because
here's what's happening. All those pods
that are being created on all those
nodes inside of your cluster, remember
inside of those pods are containers.
just exactly as we've always understood
them. What's building those containers?
Is it Kubernetes? No, absolutely not.
Because installed on every single node
inside of your cluster is going to be
some container runtime engine, whether
it's Docker or something else. Which
means if you've ever used Docker and
you've used such commands as docker run
or podman like podman run, which creates
containers, guess what? Those commands
are still running in Kubernetes, but
who's writing them? Not you. Cublet. So
Cublet, our boy that we were talking
about earlier, is what is responsible
for all of these Docker or whatever
commands that start, stop, restart,
gather information about, but they are
still using that container runtime
engine. And what that means is that the
life cycle of containers as we
understand them still absolutely apply
inside of Kubernetes. You still need a
image which is to say like a picture a
template for how a container should be
built and the application inside of it
should be set up and images still need
to come from somewhere from some place
of storage. Those are called registries
and that of course can be configured to
all sorts of different places. Now let's
put all of those moving parts together
and let's see how does it wind up that
if we say make a pod that
those now let's bring all that together
and let's see what would happen when we
actually use cube control to make a pod
inside of our cluster. Step number one
and of course we'll be doing this
ourselves like real soon. We use cube
control commands to create a pod. We'll
talk later about how you're going to
write a document called a manifest and
that will include all of these
instructions on what Kubernetes is
supposed to do and how it's supposed to
build it. So that information is taken
to the controller in this east west
diagram. You can see that right here
which of course is received by the API
server. Now you can see just how much
traffic goes to this API server. It's
quite popular. The API server will then
turn to Etsy and assuming it doesn't
just reject your pod plan outright
because there might be typos or you
might not have authorization yada yada.
If it passes all that then it will tell
hey here's the pod we're going to make.
Etsy sends back a response. 200 in HTTP
speak means thumbs up. Sounds good. API
server then sends a response back to you
at your command line saying, "Yeah,
looks good, boss. We're going to go
ahead and make that pod. But is the pod
made yet?" No, not by a long
shot. What happens next is that our API
server needs to know where is this pod
going to go? So, it goes to
theuler. And assuming that our manifest
did not say explicitly where we wanted
the pod to go, theuler is what is going
to make that decision. Let's go ahead
and put that on top of worker node
number two. So just remember worker node
two is the decision that got made that
sent back to the API server. API versus
server says, "Okay, sounds good. I'm
going to let ETCD know that we're going
to put that pod on node two." CD says,
"Sounds good, boss." And then API server
says to the scheduler, "Hey, good pick.
We're going to wind up going with node
two." So it's a lot of back and forth.
All right. as we are ascertaining where
resources are going to be located
physically inside of our
cluster. From there, our API server,
which again is inside of our controller
node, is going to reach out to the
worker node where we decided we wanted
to make the pod in the first place.
Remember how we said that that might
have been worker node number two.
So the API server sends that to Cublet,
specifically Cublet on worker node
number two. Cublet says, "Got it, boss."
And then turns around and runs all of
the necessary commands like docker run
or container dart like whatever the
command is. It's cublet that's handling
that for us. And as a result, it is only
at that moment that a container is
actually built. And it's also cublet
that's responsible for making the pod
that the container was put in. So it's
not a question of which came first,
chicken or the egg. It's definitely
clear pod is made first, container is
made inside of it second. And what
Cublet will constantly do is that it
will be feeding status updates as the
container is being built, as the
container is finished, as the container
enters an error or stop state. Cublet is
perpetually providing that information
back to the API server, which then will
in turn make sure that that information
is being recorded to ETC. So, it's a
really nifty little ecosystem of what's
happening here. And having an
understanding of what these components
are and how they work together can
really help you troubleshoot and better
understand how to make the resources and
make sure that they are working and
healthy inside of your cluster. So, very
shortly we're going to be creating
objects. What you're seeing here is an
example of how to do that by writing a
file called a manifest. So, a manifest
like making a pod like you're seeing
here just provides a list of
descriptions of these are all the things
that I want. So, it pretty much is the
same concept as you're going to your
local coffee shop and you're punching
into your app like make sure that it's
oat milk and that oh there's this this
and this topping and oh, leave room for
I don't know. But point is that's really
all that a manifest is just writing out
this is what I want and this how I want
it put together. Now the problem is is
that manifests are written in the YAML.
If you don't know how YAML is written or
edited, let's talk about that. If you
already know about YAML, feel free to
skip this section. All right. When
you're working with YAML, there are two
different types of data that you need to
be aware of. The first is definitely the
easier. This is referring to lists or
sequences. People can call it by
different names. So imagine that what
you're seeing right there is my grocery
list. It's literally a bunch of things
that I need to get. It's separated by
commas. Fine. But in YAML, lists look
like this where every item has one of
those dashes in front of it. So it makes
it far more visible and readable. And
that's really what YAML is all about,
making it readable to human eyeballs.
The other type of data we need to know
about are dictionaries, also called
mappings. And these are very different
from the way that lists work in that
dictionaries are all about key value
pairs. It doesn't matter what order
these key value pairs are in unlike a
list. But what you're seeing there in
blue are all my keys. What I'm going to
put inside of white right here, let's
say chocolate flavor. That is the value
to the key flavor. Like what brand of
ice cream do I want to have? Hershey's
or you know when I'm buying something in
the store I don't want it to like expire
any sooner than like June 30th for
instance. So notice that there is that
colon that separates the key from the
value. And you can have key value pairs
that are for instance booleans. Like
here I've got true. And if I'm trying to
say calories like about a,000 calories
for a carton seems a small price to pay.
You can have all sorts of different
values like that. Okay. So now we can
see what lists and dictionaries look
like inside of YAML. But here's the
thing, they compound. They get more
difficult. They get nested. A lot of
stuff starts happening. Let me show you
a few more things. So flavor, brand,
expiration, and all this other stuff.
These are all describing my ice cream,
right? So what I might choose to do is I
would say that ice cream is the key. The
value of ice cream is all this stuff.
Like that's what's describing it, right?
Like how am I to say that everything I
have highlighted is the value of ice
cream. Think by hitting it with an
indentation. Indentation is critically
important in YAML. It implies ownership.
And I'm in Notepad++ here. Notice that
there's this little button that I can
use to collapse. This makes it very
visible in showing you that, hey, all of
this data is the value of this key. And
where things start to really get fun is
when you have nested values inside of
others. So, under ice cream, I'm writing
out my flavor and brand of ice cream.
But maybe I would like to include what
toppings I want on top of that ice
cream. Here's the thing. Maybe I want a
list of toppings. Maybe I want
sprinkles. Maybe I want some fudge.
Maybe I want a cherry and some whipped
cream on top. Notice how that list of
dashes is indented under toppings.
Toppings is just another one of those
keys that's indented under ice
cream. When you look at manifests, they
all follow these rules. And any
indentation or dashes that you see are
there for a reason. And we'll talk about
why that is when we explore some of
these other manifests in a little bit.
All right. So, let's talk about making
manifests. Certainly, at first, what
you're going to want to do is you want
to get your manifests straight from the
source. Never ever try to write them
from scratch. What I got here is the
Kubernetes web page, and you can search
for whatever it is that you're trying to
make. So let's say pods as our first
choice. And when you often go with the
very first result, just scroll down and
you will find that there are all sorts
of different manifests for all different
ways that you can use certain resources
as well as explanations of like why and
how they work. So the first manifest
we're going to look at appropriately is
a pod. And the good news about manifests
is is that even the longer and scarier
ones, they all work pretty much exactly
the same. And once you learn how one
manifest starts to work, a lot of the
other ones start making sense as well.
What you're going to see inside of all
manifests are these three values at the
top. API version, kind, and then
metadata. Kind, fairly self-explanatory.
It tells us what kind of object we're
working with. Be careful though because
these are case sensitive. If you put in
a lowercase P for pod, oh that's just
going to cause a big big problem. So
it's little things like that that will
bite you and you'll learn very quickly.
Metadata is fairly straightforward.
Again, notice the indentation that we
talked about in YAML. Anything indented
under metadata belongs to the metadata
section. So label later when we're
working with things like labels and
annotations, those will go under the
metadata section as well. Now API
version is kind of interesting. You
might recall from when we were talking
about the architecture of a cluster
earlier that everything in Kubernetes uh
is communicated through APIs. Well,
there isn't just the one API inside of a
Kubernetes cluster. There are many. And
all of these different APIs are
configured to configure and work with
different types of objects. Version one,
which is like the most primitive API
there is. It's been around the longest,
is the one that is proficient at
creating pots. So, it is super important
that you get the API version value here
correct or you're going to get some sort
of error where it says API version D
cannot support whatever type of object
you're trying to make. And then that
brings us down to spec, which of course
is short for
specification. This is where you get to
put in your order, so to speak, of this
is how I want my object to be built. Now
remember a pod is just a wrapper around
a container or
containers. You can put in more than
one. Now look under line six where the
very first part right there is a dash.
Remember dashes indicate elements inside
of a list which means
d I could actually put in a list of
containers. If I wanted more than one
then I would basically just do something
like this. This is engine x2 and this is
using something else xyz. So that's the
significance of that dash there which
will be the significance of anything
including like ports like hey what ports
are open inside of that container. Let's
make a list of all those. Now of all of
the fields that we're placing inside of
a pod manifest where you certainly want
to be the most careful is right here.
Your image that name needs to be
accurate. If there is any sort of typo
like I did just there, you're going to
have a bad time because it's not going
to find that image. It's going to try to
find engine
X and it's going to cause errors. That
happens to everybody, but forewarned is
foremed. Okay, so in a moment we're
going to start building our first pods
here. And before we can do that, there
are a bunch of really fundamental cube
control commands that we need to know.
cube control get is the most basic there
is. It returns a list of whatever object
it is that you're asking for. If I type
cube control get pod, I'm getting back
this no resources found. That doesn't
mean that there's no pods running inside
of my cluster at all. Notice that what
it's saying is no resources found in
default namespace. We're going to talk
more about namespaces later, but suffice
it to say in our current namespace, no
other pods exist. So, we need to change
that. So, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to create a manifest here. Pod
manifest.yaml and we're going to paste
in that manifest that we were looking at
earlier. All right, nothing new here.
Save and quit. So, what we're now going
to do is we are going to create that
pod. Now that we've got that manifest
created, now there are two different
commands you could do here. Cube control
create or cube control apply. Cube
control apply is the one that you see
more often. But basically the way that
it works is that I would like to apply
what is at this file location -f pod
manifest.yaml. And what this is going to
do is that if that pod doesn't exist, it
doesn't cube control apply will create
it. We are literally applying what is in
the manifest against the cluster. That's
what makes Kubernetes declarative, which
is nice. When we pull the trigger on
that, we got this message. Cube control
uh whatever got created. Let's do a cube
control get pods. All right. Statuses
container creating. And if we just give
that a second, eventually it should say
running. But while we're looking at cube
control get, let's take a look at what
we're seeing here. this column ready
01. If you remember from our manifest,
how many containers did we put inside of
this
pot? Just one, right? It was running
engine X. And how many of those
containers are actually in a ready
state? They are up and running. Well,
zero. This one's still being created,
right? So, if I run that cube control
get command again, now you can see it's
in a running state. It's one out of one
ready. Also, there are zero restarts.
When you see a lot of restarts on a pod,
that's a big red flag. It means that
something is causing that pod to die and
it's something that probably needs to
get fixed. All right, so now that we've
created our pod and we can see our pod,
let's talk about our next command.
cube control describe. Now cube control
describe does exactly what it sounds
like. It will describe information. And
unlike get which just returns a simple
list, this is going to give us much more
information. I'm going to describe that
pod that I just made called engine X.
And take a look at the output that I
get. That's a lot. Cube control describe
is great for double-checking if
resources have been created the way that
you anticipated them. What's also nice
is that at the bottom of a cube control
describe is this section here called
events. And if a resource is busted, if
it's not working, describe should be the
first tool that you reach for because
you'll often see somewhere inside of
here what you may have goofed up and
caused it to not work. And now for our
last command, delete. All good things
must come to an end here. And let's say
that this pod needs to come down. There
are several ways that you can delete
resources, but here are two of the
easiest.
When we think of the phrase I made you,
I could destroy you. Remember how we did
apply -f with our pod manifest? We could
use cube control delete with that file
and it will delete that for us just the
same as it created it for us. That's
option number one. Option number two, if
you don't have the manifest or you don't
want to go looking for the manifest, you
can always just cube controldee. Specify
what type of object you're deleting. a
pod and then what's the name of the pod
you're trying to delete? Engine X,
right? Either way, the result is the
same. The pod will be deleted and after
I check to see, we can see that that got
removed and we've created, inspected,
and deleted a pod at this point. Next,
let's talk about namespaces, which was
coming up a little earlier. Right? If I
were to type cube control get pods right
now, it says that there are no pods
found in the default namespace, whatever
that is. But if I use my cube control
get command this time against namespace,
you can see oh default as it turns out
is literally the name of the namespace,
not like the default namespace which
happens to be XYZ, right? There are
actually many pods running inside of my
cluster right now, but I can't see them
because I'm not looking in the right
place. So check this out. When I type
cube control get pods, but this time I
specify -ashn for namespace. And let's
take a look at cube
system. Now I'm seeing some pods. Now
these pods that are running inside a
cube system are system integral pods.
They are what's holding our cluster
together. And do you remember when we
were talking about some of like the
important components that run inside of
Kubernetes like CD and theuler and
things like that? Depending on how your
cluster is built, you may actually see
pods that are running those applications
in pods inside of this namespace. Our
training environment is set up a little
bit differently. We can talk more about
that inside of the real course. But
point is is that these pods are here
because that way they are not getting
underfoot when I'm trying to create
business related pods. And also nobody
should be looking at these pods except
for admin anyway which access control is
a big big reason for wanting to use
namespaces. So that being said, it is
not difficult to make new namespaces and
I'm going to do this imperatively, which
means I'm going to make it at the
command line. Not going to use a
manifest at all. If you're planning on
taking the exams, using imperative
commands like this are a super quick and
easy way to generate certain objects.
It's what I'm going to use for my demo.
In fact, let's create this namespace and
let's just call it demo. And what I'm
going to do is I'm going to hop back
inside of that pod manifest that we were
looking at earlier. Now the thing about
manifests is is that when you are
creating objects, if you don't specify
where that object is supposed to go, it
will go to a default location. That's
set by a context, but that's a
conversation for later. Something that
you can do in order to force pods or
other objects to go into certain
namespaces is to just add under metadata
namespace demo. If I were to create this
object now pod
manifest.yaml says that the pod was
created. If I try to see what pods are
currently running, I still get no
resources found. Did I screw up? No, of
course I didn't because those pods are
inside of the demo
namespace. So, think for a minute just
what an easy mistake that can be making
objects inside of incorrect name spaces
and the confusion that that can cause.
Happens to everybody, but forewarned is
forearmmed. Now, consider this a preview
of when we start getting into resource
control a little later. But remember,
Kubernetes is a shared environment and
you need to make sure that when
resources are getting created, you
aren't taking up more than your fair
share or you're preventing pods from
going hog wild and just consuming too
many resources. Well, what I'm about to
make here is a resource quota. And a
resource quota is something that
attaches to namespaces and sets the
rules. Hey, look. Here's the hard limit
of what everything inside of your
namespace is allowed to
consume. CPU one core, memory, one
gig. And what I'm also going to use this
as an opportunity to show you is is that
there's another way to specify where
resources get built. Resource quotas
attached to namespaces. So instead of
writing that under metadata, I'm just
going to type dash N demo. So when I hit
enter on this, you can now see that my
resource quota has been applied. And
again, I'm using cube control describe
to be able to confirm that. And any pods
that get created in this namespace are
now going to have to adhere to those
resource consumption rules. That's
something really cool and something
we're going to talk about a little bit
later, but again gives you some more
insight into how important name spaces
are. Let's swing back and let's talk
about that API version line which is
inside of all manifests again. Now, as
you can see, I wrote something entirely
ridiculous right there. There is no API
version honkabonka in Kubernetes. At
least not yet. But point is is that I
want you to imagine that this is the
scenario. The day is yesterday. This
manifest worked. Version honkabanka is
good. Each and every one of these
different parameters that you set were
all accurate. Things were doing well.
Today we rolled out a new cluster at a
later version than the one we had
yesterday. Suddenly your manifests don't
work. And suddenly you're getting
messages that look like this. There are
no matches for kind pod in version
honkabona which is the hilarious message
that I actually want to see. Yeah, there
we go. I thought version two was too
boring. So what is this saying? Remember
Kubernetes communicates everything
through APIs. And when you are upgrading
Kubernetes, what you are upgrading are
its APIs. you are upgrading its ability
to recognize, configure and manage
different kinds of resources and those
change. So what does that mean for you?
Well, if you want to be like a real pro
at Kubernetes, like if you just want to
make everybody think you're such a pro
at it, every time that somebody talks
about upgrading a cluster, I just want
you to
go just like make that exact sound
because nobody likes upgrading clusters.
It's such a huge pain. And looking at
this deprecated API migration guide
here, just take a look with me. In
version
1.32, it's telling us that this type of
resource called a flow control, it's API
version went from v1 beta 3 to
v1. What it's also telling us is that
and it's using dot notation here.
Remember how in pods like under spec we
would set containers and then the name
of the container. Here it's saying that
for this particular object under spec is
a section called limited and under that
is a key called nominal concurrency
shares. Right? It's telling us that its
default values are changing. All right.
So that's what happens as you go from
version to version of Kubernetes. You
have to update your API version.
Suddenly fields might mean something
different than what they originally did
or some fields might get added or some
fields might get taken away. And you can
scroll through this and you can see all
of the different changes and that's just
the nature of the beast when you're
working with Kubernetes. Let's talk
about resource management next. So a
Kubernetes cluster is an aggregate of
all the nodes that areworked together in
order to create one hole. And what you
have to be doing is constantly keeping
an eye on how many resources are being
consumed and setting up reasonable
guideposts and guard rails to make sure
that isn't being exceeded. There are
lots of third-party tools that you can
integrate into Kubernetes. like some of
them really pretty and really visual,
but there are a few that you can uh
install that are easily used, even the
most vanilla of setups. Cube control top
is one of them, but cube control top, if
you are building a cluster from scratch,
chances are it's not going to work.
You're going to get this error metrics
API not available. What we need to do is
that we need to apply this uh manifest
here which is provided by a GitHub repo
from Kubernetes. And what that's doing
is making a whole bunch of objects. Some
of which we'll talk about inside of this
course, some of which we won't, although
we will of course inside of the full
course. Um, we need to give that a
minute to spin up. But what I just did
is that I just created a bunch of pods
that are gathering and harvesting
information about other pods in the
nodes inside of our cluster. These uh
cluster roles and roll bindings and
cluster roll bindings are what are
giving those pods permission to do that.
And the stuff about service accounts and
stuff can wait uh for a little later.
Point is is that we want that to run for
a little bit. And I'll just kind of
pause here for a second and let it
finish
up. There we go. Once that API service
uh metrics is telling us that, hey, I'm
up and running. True. Now I can start
using cube control top. So here's that
cube control top nodes command again.
Check it out. It's telling me what
percentage of available CPU and memory
has been used on the nodes inside of my
cluster. That's really nice. What's an
also a nice use case for cube control
top is pods. If I were to cube control
top pods, remember just like with cube
control get and describe, it's only
going to look for pods in the current
namespace. I don't have any pods in my
current namespace. So what I can do is I
can type top pods all name spaces or if
you want to look
cool dash capital a and here we can see
that uh the pigs of our uh cluster are
definitely these two calico pots. That's
to be expected. They are our networking
uh what's holding our nodes together
basically. But this is a great tool to
like quickly see like which of your pods
are like just out of control consuming
the most resources which is a great way
to troubleshoot and figure out what
needs to be done to rectify the
situation. All right, a little death by
PowerPoint here, but we're going to
continue talking about resource control.
What we're going to be doing really soon
is that we are going to be editing our
pod manifests and we're going to give
them more parameters and we're going to
make them more in line with the way that
we want them to behave. Specifically, we
want them to behave themselves when it
comes to resource consumption. And it's
a fine line to walk, right? Because the
containers inside of your pods, they
need resources to live. You don't want
them to starve to death. But at the
other hand, you don't want them to be
pigs. You don't want them to consume
more than they need. So there are ways
to set those. Requests are a parameter
that you can set inside of your manifest
that guarantees that your pod has a
certain amount of resources. That's good
because otherwise your containers are
going to starve. Give them the give them
the oxygen, man. They need to breathe.
And then there are limits. It's not
unheard of for containers to just go a
muck and just start consuming like rogue
like amounts of resources. Limits are
what put a hard cap on how many
resources containers can shove inside of
their face. I think that's much easier
to understand because I'm pretty sure we
can all uh
identify. All right, so what would it
look like adding these on to our
manifest? Let's take a look. Now it's
important to note that when we are
controlling the amount of resource
consumption here, look at the level of
indentation. Do you see how we are
adding this section to this particular
container? So requests and limits are
set on a container by container basis.
Make sure that that's clear. And under
resources is where we can add those two
sections, requests and limits. And
indented under that is where you can
control. All right, what's the minimum
amount of resources as far as maybe CPU
and memory is concerned? I want my pods
to have at least let's say 65 uh
megabytes of memory. And when it comes
to CPU, here's something unique to
Kubernetes.
If one core is equal to
1,000 millore, the heck is that? Millor
allows you to like further specify
there's only so much of the CPU timing
that I want to use. I don't want to use
a full core. I can actually say at the
very least make sure that I get
250 mil core worth of
CPU. And pretty much the same thing
applies down here at the bottom, except
limits must be at least the same as the
requests. I would get an error if I
tried to set the limit lower. But let's
set a limit of 500 and let's set a
memory of 130. Basically doubling it.
And if I were to create this object
right now, it would work.
Now let's take a look back at that name
space we were looking at earlier. Do you
remember when I put a resource quota on
top of it saying that uh hey any uh pods
that get created inside of this
namespace are going to have to follow
the rules. Well, watch this. If I put a
watch on here, then we can see this
happen in real time.
But I'm going to go ahead and create
this pod here. And I'm going to put it
inside of the demo
namespace. The second that I did that,
look what
happened. Immediately that resource
quota said, "All right, you've already
consumed x amount of resources. You've
already requested that much to be used."
And what that means is is that I could
keep making more pods exactly like this
one, but only up until I reach what the
resource quota amount has been. So a
resource quota, the way that it works is
that it's kind of like the bouncer
that's standing outside of the
nightclub. All right. When you've hit
the maximum amount of people that you're
allowed to let inside of the club
because you know like there's fire code
rules or something, at that point you
start turning people away. you start
saying no, no more, we're full up, go
home. It's the same with making pods.
Let's just do an illustration real quick
to see how that changes. So suppose that
we create a pod with that request and
limit in a certain name space. We have a
resource quota where it says that hey
you can only use up to 400 megabytes in
memory, 500 megabytes in limits. Now,
what's interesting about this is is that
what the resource quota now is doing is
that it's being much more
granular. Resource control can be super
granular to the point that it's kind of
confusing, but it is possible to really
spell out in your resource quota just
exactly how high you want certain
amounts to go. So watch what happens
when we add another pod that also has a
request of 100 and a limit of 200.
Notice that with that limit of another
200, we are currently up to 400
megabytes of the 500 that we're total
allowed to have here. If I try to make
one more
pod, that is going to be in excess of
500, which means that this pod would be
denied. it would not be allowed to be
created inside of our cluster. Remember
that all Kubernetes is ultimately in the
service of maintaining containers. And
what we're going to talk about next are
probes. Now probes are basically watchd
dogs that you can put on top of your
individual pods and hence your
individual containers to basically look
out for and enforce certain behavior.
The two types of probes that everybody
should know about are readiness and
livveness probes. Now, the way that both
of these probes work is that you
start with a
container. And what's happening once you
place a probe on it is that that probe
represented by this ghost inside of this
sheet is constantly poking that
container with a
stick. The reason why it's doing that is
because every couple of seconds or so
it's going to ask, "Hey, you okay?" And
then the container is going to reply
back, "OMG, yes." And this is going to
happen over and over again forever.
That's the way that probes work. But the
thing is is that there's two different
kinds of probes. Like I said, and here's
the difference between the two. If you
are working with a livveness probe, when
the container is probed by the probe and
you get no response back at
all or the response comes too late, what
the probe will do is say, "Well, that's
a
strike." And after a predetermined
number of consecutive strikes, the probe
is going to kill the container.
Ironically enough, that's what a
livveness probe is for. Because turning
it off and turning it on again is just
one of the timehonored techniques of it
troubleshooting. Sometimes restarting
the container is exactly what you need.
Now, a readiness probe is different. It
also is checking to see if the container
is responsive. But here's what happens
with a readiness probe. It doesn't kill
a nonresponsive container.
This is the gentle parent. It's like,
"Oh, little container Timmy isn't awake
and ready to face the day yet.
Everybody, everybody, leave little Timmy
the container alone." Right? He's not
ready. I don't want any traffic to go to
him. And what's happening is is that we
are basically removing that pod from any
predetermined settings we have that
allow other pods or other resources to
communicate with it. So putting
readiness probes on things make sure
they are ready before they are actually
being
accessed. Okay. So what do these probes
look like inside of manifests? Well,
here's a pod that is running a
application simple service. It's a
testing tool and we are adding a
livveness probe which again notice is
being added at the container level. It's
not something you add to a pod. It's
something that you add to a container
inside of a pod. And I got a lot of
different settings here. And this is
where working with pro probes can get
tricky. What do these mean? Probes are
extremely granular. You get a lot of
control over how you want these things
to act. Let's start down here on lines
17, 18, and 19. First thing that we need
to determine is what is the method of
the probe like how is like what's the
stick that the probe is using to tap the
container. Well, the simple service uh
application here is an API which means
it can actually receive HTTP requests.
So the way that we're testing that we're
probing is that we are sending get
requests to a particular endpoint at a
particular port inside of the
container. Not all containers are going
to handle this particular method of
probing. There are lots of different
things that you can do, however. So
we'll just leave it at that. But what do
these other parameters up here mean?
Well, initial delay seconds too means
how soon after creation are we
probing like how many seconds are we
going to let it get on its feet before
we go tap tap you
okay two seconds period seconds this is
asking how often thereafter are we
probing so basically what's happening is
is that the pod is created. Then two
seconds goes by and then there is a
probe. Then another five seconds goes by
and then there is a probe and then after
another 5 seconds well you get that that
just repeats forever.
So the uh delay in probes can be
significant because if you're probing
all the time then that makes for more
highly likelihood that you're going to
wind up finding an
error. Speaking of errors, timeout
seconds. How long we giving the
container to respond? So after I tap it,
tap tap. You
okay? All right. Here I'm saying you've
got one second to send me back a
response to my HTTP get in this example
that you are
okay and failure threshold. What this is
saying is is how many consecutive and
that is important consecutive failures
before we kill this not pod container
because that is ironically what livess
probes do. They kill
containers. All right. And uh obviously
you can tweak these like using all sorts
of different parameters and hopefully
that's making it clear. Make sure you're
reading the documentation when you are
creating
probes. And what's super nice is is that
the difference between writing a
livveness probe and a readiness probe is
virtually
nil. I could leave this exactly as is
written. But now the behavior is
different. What would happen is is that
after I get three consecutive failures
to get a response from this pod, it
would turn off traffic. It would turn
off traffic to that pod until the probe
was satisfied after more probes that
okay, now it's, you know, answering and
now I can allow traffic to go back to
it. So, make sure you know the
difference between readiness and
livveness. What I'm about to do is an
exercise in futility. It's to teach you
that, hey, what I'm doing is great in
testing, but is not something you'd want
to do in production. And it's also going
to introduce a really important concept
we're going to be getting into next.
Plus, I'm going to show you some cool
new cube control commands. Cube control
run is a quick and dirty way to create
pods without using a manifest. So, this
is going to make a pod called demo pod.
It's going to use the engine X image
inside of it. And a neat command that I
can use is port forward. If I use port
forward against a pod, which is named
demo pod, I can choose a local port, one
that's on my local machine to connect to
the container port inside of the enginex
container
itself. Now the container port that's
written in stone. Engine X its
containers are exposed for HTTP on port
80. For local port, it could be any TCP
port that's available on your system. Uh
I'm going to use port
2224. Now when I hit enter with that
command, it is going to hog up my
command line. Now I have T-Mox, so I'll
just split my screen. And by the way,
for the exam, T-Max is installed. So you
will be able to use tricks like this if
you are studying this to plan to take
the exam. With that port forward
activated, look what I can do. I can
curl
localhost port
2224. What's happening here is is that
I'm going to the local port that's
connected to the container port that's
inside of the pod. How cool is this?
Welcome to Engine X. This is the HTML.
This is literally the welcome page for
what's running inside of this container
inside of my cluster. You got to kind of
be a nerd to get excited by that, but
heck, guilty.
Anyway, press control C and that'll stop
the port forward. And that means that if
I were to try to curl localhost 2224
again, I'm going to get a failed to
connect. Now, point is is that I want to
make a configuration change to how this
container works. So, there are a couple
of different ways you could do this. I'm
going to use a cube control exec
command. And what I'm going to do is I'm
going to open up an interactive terminal
inside of my pod which was called demo
pod. And what that terminal is going to
be is a bash shell. So I'll just type sh
like so. And check it out. My command
line has changed. I am inside of my
engineext container right now. And if I
needed to make any sort of, you know,
configuration changes or things like
that, I could. For instance, let's make
a uh inside of var, let's make a www
directory. And inside of that, I'm going
to create a new custom
uh index page. So, let's just echo help.
I'm stuck in a container and I can't get
out. That's what I want to be my little
welcome page, right? I'm going to put
that inside of var www inside of
index.html. Now, making that change, uh,
you'll wonder, well, I didn't use Vim or
something like that. Well, where's Vim
installed? Not inside of this container.
If I try to use Vim or whatever, it's
not going to work. So, if you are using
CubeControl Exec to open up a shell,
just be in mind, you're kind of limited
to the tools that are inside of that
container at the moment. But again,
remember this is an exercise in
futility. All right, I'm going to leave
that open because I'm going to be using
uh my other command line here to make a
change. What I've got is a configuration
file here,
engineext.config. That will change the
way that this container works. What I
need to do is get it from here to there.
So, here's a neat trick. CubeControl
copy allows you to take local files or
files that are remote that are inside of
the pod and you can copy them in and
out. I'm going to go ahead and copy
enginex config. I'm going to put that
inside of demo pod and we're going to
put that inside of the var www
directory. No, excuse me. We're going to
put that inside of the Etsy uh enginex
directory. Uh and that enginex.config
config file that I'm copying in will
replace the one that was already there.
So, I can confirm that by just checking,
hey, inside of the Etsy engine X
directory, is that EngineX config file
changed? Yeah, all these comments are
telling me that that's my custom little
file. And what it's going to do is that
it's going to use that custom index that
I made at var www. All right. This is
just showing you like the method behind
my madness here. This is not anything
that's like like super essential to
understand uh how Engine X works. But
here's what we have to do. I need to in
order for that to work
uh reload Engine X. That's going to kick
in those changes. So if that worked, we
should now be able to do this. I'm going
to exit back out and let's run that port
forward one more
time. Let's do a curl at
localhostport
2224. And check it out. I have created
an index file that's custom. I created a
configuration file that points to it. I
made both of those changes inside of my
container using some pretty neat uh uh
cube control commands, except ah
ah oh. Oh, excuse me. I seem to have
deleted my pot. Oops. Well, I could
always just remake it, right? Cube
control run demo pod and let's use the
image engine X. All right, there we go.
Pod's back just like it was. I can
reopen my port forward. I could run my
curl command again.
And whoa, what
happened? Ah, I lost all my work. None
of it persisted. All right, this is why
this is a, you know, show and not do
situation. Great for testing and when
you're figuring this stuff out, but the
fact that that didn't work is that it is
because containers are stateless. All
those changes were made to the old
container. The old container is dead.
It's gone. And the changes that were
made with it are dead and gone, too. So,
how are we supposed to take ephemeral
things like pods and containers that die
constantly? And are we able to push
configurations to it? Glad you asked
because that's the next thing we're
going to take a look at. All right,
let's do a little animation to help make
this point clear. So you saw what
happened that I made that enginex config
file inside of that container. Problem
is is that when that container and pod
go away, it is going to take that file
with it. So obviously that's not a
solution. We can't have engineext.config
inside of the
container. Where then? I mean it's going
to have to be somewhere else. In
Kubernetes there exists a type of object
known as a config map. This is a whole
other type of resource that you can make
using a manifest just like you can make
pods. And inside of config maps is where
you can put pieces of data like
configuration files or environment
variables or really any sort of thing
that you think might need to be changed
about how future versions of pods may
need to be configured. It makes it super
easy to make those changes in a way
that's disengaged from the container
that you are attempting to uh adjust.
Now, what we're going to be seeing here
is that making config maps are very
easy. Attaching config maps to
containers uh that's something of a
different story. If you already have
experience working with Docker and
volumes, great because this is going to
transfer 100%.
But if not, no worries. Let me explain
it to you. The config map, which
remember has the config file inside of
it, will be mounted as a volume to the
pod
itself. Once that volume has been
mounted to the pod, we then mount the
volume to the container. and the volume
is mounted to the container at a
specific mount point which is going to
be some arbitrary directory inside of
the container
itself. Now what's super magical about
this is is that remember you may have
many different pods that are all
identical and they all require the same
configuration.
Well, hey, take that one config map and
you can mount that to as many pods as
you want. So, configuration changes only
need to be made in just one place.
That's super advantageous. You're going
to be seeing config maps an awful lot.
Now, let's see what it would take in
order to write a manifest that would
actually pull this off. All right, step
number one. Let's make a config map. As
you can see, there's already one config
map right here that we don't need to
worry about. and we're going to cheat a
little bit. We're going to use a
cubecontrol create command in order to
make it. First, I need to make a file.
Let's create a txt file.
Heroes.txt. Let's put a couple of my
favorite heroes inside of here. All
right. Superman, Batman, Wonder Woman,
Flash. Yep, looks good. If I were to do
a cube controlcreate config map or again
if you want to look like a pro use the
shortand
cm. I'm gonna create a config map that
I'm going to call dem heroes. Why? I
don't
know. I'm going to create that config
map from the file that I just made
heroes.txt. And there's a new
config map in
town. Dem heroes. Notice data one means
that there's one piece of data inside of
it. Does that mean you can put multiple
things inside of one config map? Yes,
you can. Do people often do that? No,
not really. Unless it's environment
variables. If I were to run cube control
describe against that particular config
map, look at what we see here. Ah, the
contents of that config file are present
just as text inside of the object
itself. So you're not putting anything
huge inside of config maps literally
text files are the only thing big big
things like database that's something
about persistent storage and that's a
whole different
conversation. Now let's hop inside of
our pod manifest from earlier. Let's not
worry about resource control and all
that stuff and let's figure out how are
we going to get that config map attached
to this pot. Step number one, we need to
add that config map that we made as a
volume to this pot. You really got to
mind your P's and Q's when it comes to
indentation with this, which is why it
may be easier just to go to
Kubernetes.io, find under the config map
page a manifest that already has all
this written down. So, survival tip for
the exam because you could save yourself
a lot of heartache that way. But what
you'd see there and what I'm going to do
here is I'm going to create a section
called volumes. That's right under the C
and containers under spec because
remember this is being added at the pod
level. You can add as many volumes as
you want. Give the volume whatever name
you want as long as it is unique. Those
were all DC characters from earlier,
right? So let's name the volume DC
Heroes. Although I really I could have
called it
anything. And what we're putting inside
of that volume is a config map. Note the
capital
M. Boy, let me tell you how many times
I've been burned by that. But camel
casing is definitely a thing in
Kubernetes and it will bite you if you
are not careful. Now, uh, the config map
that we created, remember its name is
dem heroes. So we're going to put dem
heroes right there. So step one is
complete. We've added the config map as
a volume to this pod. Step number two,
we need to add that volume to the
container itself. So again, mind your
indentation. I'm right here under the I
in image along with everything else that
I'm putting inside of that container.
I'm adding a section called volume
mounts. And the dash remember means
elements in a list. I could mount
multiple volumes to this one container.
I'm basically making a list of those. So
first I need to put what is the name of
the volume that I'm
mounting. Remember how we called it DC
heroes. So make sure that you are
capitalizing correctly and doing all
that correctly. Boom. Done.
Next we need to specify all right where
in this engine X container is this
volume going to be mounted that is what
we set by the mount
path and what's super cool about mount
path is is that if you choose a
directory that definitely does not exist
heroes da does not exist inside of the
engineext container as you can well
imagine
But with all that done, let's split our
screen here and let's create this pod.
All right, need to delete this pod here
real
quick. And let's make this pod as we see
it
here. Demo pod is created. Give it a
second to come online. All right, I'm
going to use cube control exec to hop
inside of that pod. And I want to show
you right here.
Aha, there's a new directory in town.
Heroes. So, mount path clearly makes
these directories if they don't exist.
And if I hop inside of the heroes
directory, here's where I want you to
take a guess. What's going to be inside
of that directory?
Oh, the mount path's connected to the
volume. The volume's connected to the
config map. The config map contains a
file. The name of that file is
heroes. So, if we look, check it out.
There's all of our heroes. They're
showing up inside of the container. And
what's super nice is is that as long as
this config map is up and running, I can
delete and recreate this pod all the
live long day, that heroes.txt file will
always be there inside of that specific
directory inside of my pod. Now, it
ain't all sunshine and rainbows when it
comes to volumes. Here is a very common
mistake. Suppose that I want that file
heroes.txt. I want to show I want that
to show up inside of a specific
directory like inside of a directory
that already exists. Let's put it in
that Etsy engineext directory where that
engineext.config file is located. Right?
If I were to really quick delete this
pod because I'm going to
uh because I'm going to recreate it here
in just a
second. Cube control apply. Pod is
created. But when I check get pods,
uhoh wamp, we got an
error. What you should be reaching for
every time that there is an error, first
thing is you're going to want to use
your describe. But when we take a look
at the description here, it tells us we
made the container, but it backed off,
restart, it just wasn't successfully
able to run. So cube control describe
isn't really helping me here. It's not
telling me what's wrong. But this
will cube control
logs is a cool command that we'll talk
more about later that allows you to
gather uh the standard output and the
standard error that are generated by
containers inside of your cluster. And
when I look at this one container pod
and the logs that it's got, it's saying,
"Hey, I tried to open
enginex.config, but I couldn't. I
couldn't find that file or
directory. Do uh do you think it's a
coincidence that that can't be found
when that's the exact directory where we
put our volume? No, of course not.
Because uh here's what's happening.
Mount paths will
overwrite existing
directories. And I know what you're
saying because students say it to me all
the time. Well, Chad, what if you were
to put like uh
heroes.txt at the end of mount path?
That would just create a directory
called
heroes.txt. That would work. Uh but uh
probably not what you're looking to do
because now your file is in a wrong
directory. So, no, that won't work. It's
in circumstances like this that you have
to use what's called a sub path. And
basically the way that I would explain a
subpath is this. Let me type it out.
There you go. Subpath means that instead
of like mapping the entire contents of
the entire config map to the entire
directory at C EngineX, let's write a
subpath to just a file inside of the
config map, which remember it's called
heroes.txt. txt. That's what's inside of
our config map. And we want to mount
that file to
heroes.txt inside of the Etsy engine X
directory. So with that subpath now in
place, let's delete our pod here. Let's
recreate it and let's hop inside of it
and let's see if it's working. First of
all, it is. Looks good. Cube control
exec. It's here somewhere. If I hop
inside of uh Etsy engine X, you can now
see that our heroes.txt file is now
peacefully coexisting alongside all the
other files that are inside of this
directory. So use subpath when you need
to write to a directory where other
files are present because otherwise it's
just going to obliterate the whole
thing. The natural progression from
having learned about config maps is to
start talking about secrets because
secrets and config maps are very
similar. They both take information and
store it inside of themselves rather
than storing it inside of the container.
The difference is is that secrets are
well secrets. They are things like
passwords, tokens, keys like generally
sensitive information.
Now, uh, secrets are created through an
almost identical process to config maps.
So, there's little to learn here, but
there are certain warnings that I do
want to give you about using secrets.
Secrets on their own are not encrypted.
They're stored in the API server inside
of EDC, right? And anybody who has API
access who can see that secret like
inside of your cluster, they'd need cube
control to do it, but they'd be able to
see it or change it or anything like
that. Kubernetes does require you to use
your own encryption solution, which is
not something that we're going to talk
about. There's so many different ways to
do it out there, but just so you know,
secrets do not encrypt right out of the
box. The other thing to know about
secrets is is that there are many
different kinds. What we're seeing here
on this table is that there's a couple
that you can use for specific
circumstances like SSH authentication or
if maybe it's like a username password
situation with basic off. I'm going to
be using that in a demonstration here in
just a moment. These are all different
kinds. The generic type of secret is one
that's just opaque. It's meant to like
be, hey, this is just some random like
file or something and we don't want
people to be able to see what's inside
of it. All right, so here's a manifest
for a change of how to create a secret.
And secrets are namespaced just like
config maps and pods are. So make sure
that your secrets are in the same name
spaces as the pods that want to use
them. Same is true for config maps. And
what I'm going to do is that I'm just
going to encrypt a secret uh password.
Alta three is the value of the key
password. And the type of secret that
I'm using is basic off. Now you could
like we were doing with a config map
earlier use a cube control create
command to do this. There's often you
know imperative ways of doing that. You
would just have to spell out what type
of secret is it and then hey we are
putting in the uh environment well the
call it environment variable put the
keyword uh value uh from literal. So
from literal is something you can use
also when you're making config maps.
Just makes it easy to put key value
pairs inside of objects. But uh we won't
be doing that. Let's just go ahead and
uh create this secret from this
manifest. And uh let's make sure that
it's saved otherwise that won't work.
All right, there we go. So secrets can
be listed out just like anything else uh
that we make. But if I were to describe
what is inside of that secret, my SQL
secret, notice that it tells us that
hey, there's a key password, but it
doesn't show us what the value is.
Remember, this is not secure. I
absolutely could crawl inside of this
particular object and see uh what that
password value is. All right. So, you
need further encryption for this to
work, but we can go ahead and take this
to the next step. All right. What we're
about to do is we are about to read in
the contents of that secret so that it
can be used inside of this MySQL uh
database that we're putting together
inside of this container. And everything
you're about to see here could also be
used with a config map. So, again,
secrets config maps very interchangeable
in how you can do things. Uh, one of the
keywords you can set for a container is
environment variables. So if there was
an environment variable called my SQL
root password and there is the MySQL
image has that environment variable
already defined inside of it. You could
just go ahead and say that the value is
alt to
three. Yeah, that'd be dumb. Yeah, let's
just put our passwords right in plain
text inside of our manifest, said nobody
ever. My god, all of the security people
just had a stroke. No, instead what
we're going to do is we're going to say
that, hey, the value of that environment
variable is going to be taken from a
secret a secret key that is referred to
by the following name. Now, do you
remember what the name of our secret
was? Cube control get secrets. Yeah, it
was called my SQL secret. So that's that
right there. And inside of that secret,
remember we want alt to three to be the
value for that variable.
Right? So inside of this secret right
here, we are looking for what key points
to that
value
password. Right? So, what I'm going to
have to do down here on the left side is
that I'm going to say that the key we're
looking for is literally called password
inside of that
secret. All right. So, uh with all that
in place and if I were to save this and
go ahead and create my pod at this
point, pods created. Might take a second
to get stood up. Whoop control get pods.
All right. - W stands for wait. It means
just give me updating output like as
changes are made. We'll continue once
this is up. Oh man, underestimated that.
Okay, so it is up and running now, which
goes to show containers don't always
spin up
instantaneously. We're going to uh do a
cube control exec inside of this
container. Let's test whether or not
this worked.
I'm just going to for the sake of
demonstration use the echo command on
that environment variable, the one that
we set right here, which just goes to
show secrets ain't encrypted. You'll
notice that right there. You can see
that that's the password that we set
inside of our secret. So, it definitely
does work. Just make sure you got your
ducks in a row when it comes to actually
setting up encryption inside of your
setup. And for the exam, don't worry
about encryption. that's not something
that you'll be asked to set up. So,
something super important to know for
the sake of troubleshooting as well as
just keeping your sanity is logs. And
the way that it works is that every
container inside of a pod generates its
own logs. And the logs that are
generated are always what the standard
out and the standard error of a given
container's output may be. To
demonstrate this, take a look at this
manifest. We've got one pod that has two
containers inside of it. Both of which
are running busy box, which just means
that we can on a basically infinite loop
print out like the date as well as
whatever the value of i is. And this one
is pausing uh for one second every time
that it prints. This one is pausing for
3 seconds every time that it prints. So,
what we're bound to see is a difference
in the output that's going to be created
by both of these pods. Now, let's go
ahead and create this pod here super
quick. And once that's up, we're going
to explore this new cool cube control
command. CubeControl logs.
Now cube control logs you don't have to
specify oh that's the logs of a pod or
because that's the only thing that this
command will look up the logs of pod
containers. Now keeping that in mind if
I were to check the logs of this pod
which is called counter you got to ask
yourself what sort of output am I going
to get because there are two containers
here. If I were to pull the trigger on
that, there you can see is the output
that it's printing out the date and it's
clearly happening every second. But if I
scroll up a little bit, it says
defaulted container count out of count
and count by three. So this is just an
example of the significance of the order
in which your containers are listed.
this container was listed first.
Therefore, this container was built
first. Therefore, this container is the
one that by default we're checking the
logs on it. But the cube control logs
command is pretty versatile. There's a
lot of cool things that you can do with
it. Uh for one thing, I can do dash c to
specify I want to like get the logs
specifically for this container. And you
can see that these are in increments of
3 seconds. So this is definitely the
second container. Show you the
versatility of this just a little bit
more that uh knowing all of your options
that come with cube control logs can
really help. If we were to do all
containers, I will actually get all the
logs from both containers being output
all at once. What you might also want is
to get a stream going that these are
being generated every 3 seconds. So if I
put a dash f there on the end then you
can see that this is updating in real
time as new logs are being
added and because we are doing these in
uh increments of like a couple of
seconds. What's super cool is is that
you can also add in flags like this.
Maybe all of my logs since 10 seconds
ago. That's only just these three. So,
there's a lot of cool things that you
can do with logs, but let me show you
one other thing about the nature of logs
and their
impermanence. Because what happens is is
that when a pod gets deleted, that pod
is going to clean up after itself, which
means all of the logs are going to get
removed as well. What I'm seeing is is
that this pod is on top of node one.
This is just, you know, for your uh
education and how logs work and the
impermanence of them and why people use
third-party logging solutions to kind of
work around this. But I'm going to get
on to node one
itself and I'm going to hop inside of
the var log
directory and check it out. There's a
directory here called pods h. Let's hop
on there. Sudo CD
pods. What you complaining
about? CD
pods. All right. What's inside of
pods? All right. What you're seeing here
is that there is a directory called
pods. It is root protected. So, let's do
a little sudo here. And what you'll see
inside of it is
aha counter is the name of the pod which
is in the default name space and these
are all the other pods that must be
running on top of node two. So what that
means is is that I
could screw
it. Enough of this messing around. All
right. What I could do is is I could hop
inside of that directory here and show
you. Look at that. There are two
subdirectories, count and count by
three. Those are the names of our
manifests
uh containers, right? So just in case
you forgot, count and count by three are
the names of those containers. And if we
were to take a look inside of either of
those, there's the log file.
Now, if I were to delete that
pod, let's do a little
watch and see how long it
takes for this to delete. So, basically,
every 60 seconds or so, depending on the
cluster, Cublet will uh go and do its
rounds, we'll do clean up and things
like that. It's only a matter of time
before this directory and therefore all
the logs inside of it wind up getting
deleted. There you go. Had my eye on the
little clock there was about 45 seconds.
So that's about right. So be careful
that when you are cleaning up your pods,
you're cleaning up all the logs that go
with it. There are third party logging
tools out there. That's beyond the scope
of what we're going to talk about. But
now you know about cube control logs.
Sorry for the visual jump scare, but I'm
going to use my boine friend here to
explain this next point. What we're
going to be talking about next are
labels. And I always thought the labels
was a bad choice of term for what they
are in Kubernetes. Tags will be much
more appropriate. Uh I am from Hershey,
Pennsylvania. And what you're seeing
here is a cow that very well could be at
any of the dairy farms that are in my
neighborhood. and cow are cattle. They
are animals and they're being treated
well, but they're just one of many
inside of the herd, right? We put tags
inside of ears so that we're able to
track things like breed of like
temperament of like farm or age. Like
it's kind of like metadata that's being
put onto these ear tags that helps us
classify and be able to tell like one
cow from the next because they're just
members of the herd, right? We don't
typically keep cows as as pets. They're
cattle. And I say that respectively
because that's exactly the concept of
how things work in Kubernetes. We call
them labels, these ear tags. And you can
put them on any kind of object from pods
all the way up to nodes
themselves. And the purpose of labels is
be able to group, view, and operate like
a subsection of multiple objects all at
once. And it's one of like the primary
ways that Kubernetes objects are
identified. And labels are no big deal.
They are ser and labels are no big deal.
They're simply key value pairs. So if
you take a look here under metadata, we
have labels. There are one, two, three,
four labels inside of this manifest.
They must be key value pairs. They can
be pretty much whatever you want. Uh the
best labels are descriptive and unique.
And you got to be careful as you're
going to find out about putting the
wrong label on the wrong object. that
can lead to some uh definitely not good
unintended consequences. But it's really
easy to add and remove these labels.
Let's talk about that before we start
using them in real practice. So let's
take a look at creating some pods with
labels and see how we can manipulate and
use them. So let's make a pod. And as
you can see from our manifest there,
it's dead simple. And you'll also see in
the manifest that there's no mention of
any labels being put on this whatsoever.
We're going to go ahead and create this
pod. And I want to show you that if I
were to type cubecontrol getpods
d-show labels, it'll give us the typical
get pods output. But now there's also
this column labels none. You can see we
did not put any inside of the manifest.
First thing we need to know is how to
change, update, or remove labels on our
pods and other objects. So, let's just
get a little stream going so we can see
this update in real time. There we
go. First method is to go and edit the
actual manifest itself. So, under
metadata, labels. Remember, labels are
definitely always key value pairs. So,
cool beans. That's what I want to do. If
I do a cube control apply, that's a
totally legal change. Kubernetes is
happy to make changes to running pods.
And as you can see up there, it's got
the label cool beans on it. But there
are other ways to add or even remove or
update labels on top of pods, and those
are using specific cube control
commands. So, cube control label. I'm
going to label that pod, which is called
demo pod. And let's throw another label
on there. Let's say that I want the
label awesome sauce. Be careful though,
because when you're working with labels
at the command line, you can't use
colons like you would in a manifest. You
got to use that equal sign. And that
will add to the existing labels that are
already there. Now there's no limit to
the number of labels realistically that
you can put on given
objects. But if you try to put some
other label where the first part the key
is something that's already a label on
the object. So awesome training that's
what this is. Ah I got this error that
says that oh no that key awesome already
has a value. So you can update labels if
you want to change them. If I want
awesome value to be training, then I
would just add d- overwrite onto that.
And you can see it changes it. You could
also make this change in the manifest.
As far as removing labels goes, uh,
that's super simple. All you have to do
is just take that command there, include
just the key, the first part, and put
that minus sign on the end. So that's
removing awesome and now I'm removing
cool and now all the labels are gone.
When you'll see later when we're talking
about deployments and services and
things like that, these are other types
of objects that are highly dependent on
labels. So being proficient at like
manipulating them is super important.
Now there's one last thing I want to
show you that is really neat about how
to work with labels. I use this a lot
and I think it might
help.
Dashl, we're going to put this on our
cube control get command. Dashl allows
us to add a column where at the top we
have the key. So let's say that the key
is alt
3. Check that out. See how there's a
column there called alta 3. Let's label
this pod and let's add alt to three
equals
awesome. Notice that that's showing up.
And if I were to create another pod,
let's just call another pod. This one is
using also the engine X image, then
notice that it's blank.
So, in the occasion that you need to
compare pods and like see which ones
have a certain label and which ones
don't, that can be a lot cleaner of an
output. And it's something that I use in
my label work. Oh, almost forgot. Now,
uh the other thing about labels is is
that it enables us to do things like
trigger multiple objects all that have
uh the same label on them. So, I'm going
to create another pod here. And I'm
going to label that pod called another
pod. And let's put the label alt to
three equals awesome on top of that one
as well. All right, we have three pods
here that are totally not connected in
the least. And when you are working
inside of a like productionsiz cluster,
you're going to be dealing with hundreds
of pods, many many pods. How are you
supposed to pick out from the haystack
all the needles that you need? Well,
that's what's nice about this. We can
use selector that I want to only grab
those pods that have the label alt3
equals awesome. See how it's only
returning those pods. That's important.
And like I said before, tools like
deployments and services use labels like
this to kind of sus out which pods
they're looking for. Let's talk about
the brutal inevitability of what happens
to pods. All pods die. They are not
meant to last forever. And pods can die
for any number of reasons, like due to
fluctuations in traffic or errors or
when you're trying to make updates.
Point is, you should never expect pods
to stick around. But what you probably
would want is that if a pod were to be
taken down, like due to an error or like
suppose one of your nodes goes down, you
want it to come back, right? Well, if I
were to delete one of the pods that
you're seeing here, that pod's going to
get deleted, but it ain't coming back,
right? Definitely not bulletproof, one
would say. which is why creating pods
inside of production environments, pods
are rarely ever created on their own.
Instead, they are made as part of
deployments. So, check this out. We're
going to create a deployment. We'll take
a look at the manifest in a little bit.
Let's call this demo deploy. And I want
this to use engine X because it's a
simple and easy one to build. And check
that out. It made a pod named after the
deployment. If I type cube control get
deploy or deployment if you're feeling
fancy. Notice that it's writing that
out. It's also saying that one out of
one is ready. Ah, how interesting thing
is is that deployments are able to
create multiple clones of the same pod
called replicas. and putting the cart
before the horse a little bit here. I'm
going to use a command cube control
scale. There's other ways to do this,
but I'm going to take that deployment
called demo deploy. And I want the
number of replicas to go from one to
three. And look what's happening at the
top of my screen here. All right, we got
two more pods joining the battle. And
what's going to happen is that this
deployment is going to ultimately make
sure that there are three pods, no more,
no less, constantly running inside of
our cluster. And here's what's really
cool. Delete pods all whack. These pods
are all getting deleted, including those
two little demo pods earlier. But look
what happened. The deployment replaced
them. So, what you're seeing here
already are two of the biggest
advantages of deployments. The fact that
it allows you to scale. I can add more
of a pod or I could scale down. I could
get less of a pod. Let's take it back
down to one. And if any of my pods
should die, and they're not supposed to,
the deployment is going to make sure
that they come right back. Now, what can
be tricky about deployments at first is
their manifest. It's slightly longer
than what we're used to seeing. so far
in this course. But not to fear because
what you're seeing here is a basic pod
manifest, right? We've seen this plenty
of times by this point. What a
deployment does is that we take away
certain parts of that pod manifest. For
instance, we don't need to worry about
naming the pods. So that part of the
metadata, we're just taking that right
out. Remember, the pods are going to be
named after the deployment that makes
them. So, that's something to keep in
mind. The new stuff is what you're
seeing here up at the top. And let's
break down exactly what it is that we're
seeing. There are two metadata sections
inside of this manifest. Don't get those
confused. Uh, the one that you're seeing
up here is the manifest for the
deployment, and this is the manifest for
the pod. Remember, deployments make
pods. That is their goal. So part of the
deployment manifest will be the manifest
for the pods that it's making.
Right? All right.
Now deployments can have labels too.
Anything in Kubernetes can have labels,
but it's not required. So don't worry
about that too much. Spec. Again, this
is spec for the deployment as opposed to
spec for the pod, which is down at the
bottom.
And here you're seeing that when I was
using cube control scale at the command
line to increase or decrease or set the
number of replicas a deployment had.
That's a number that you can set inside
of the manifest itself. And you can
totally edit the manifest and do a cube
control apply. That will increase or
decrease whatever the number of replicas
to whatever that number may be. Now
here's where things get really super
important. Remember when we were talking
about labels about how labels are used
by many objects in Kubernetes to
identify like to access other resources.
That is exactly what's happening right
here. We have a deployment that's
basically saying all right listen up all
of the pods I will select them that
match the following label app engine X.
If you have that label, you belong to
me. Engine X deployment. Robble robble.
Robble. All right. So that's important.
Okay. Our deployment is saying any pod
that has that label on it belongs to
that
deployment. And what you'll notice
is template is where we uh start
describing, okay, what's the template
for the pods that are going to get
created by this deployment. Notice that
part of that template includes putting
the label app engine X on any of these
pods. That's required otherwise they
won't even be recognized by the
deployment itself. So let's build this
deployment using this manifest and let's
take another look at it at the command
line. Okay, I'm going to go ahead and I
am going to create the manifest that you
see right here. And immediately you can
see that there are one, two, three pods
spinning up because that's how many we
said we wanted to have for replicas. I'm
using this dashl
uh part of my get pods here which is
giving us this column app engine x. And
remember we said that all of the
deployment pods need to have the label
app engine x and that is clearly what we
are doing right here. Now, I'm going to
show you a few things. First of all,
just uh if I were to take the number of
replicas here and change it from three
to two, making that change inside of the
manifest, then running cube control
apply will cause the number of replicas
to change. Same as when I was using cube
control scale. The other thing that I
want to show you using some of those
cube control label commands we were
doing earlier is this. I'm going to grab
one of those deployments, the very first
deployment. And notice that, of course,
they got these random characters. That's
to make sure that each pod has its own
unique name. That's a dead giveaway that
this is a pod made by a deployment or
something similar. I'm going to take
that first pod and I'm going to take the
label app engine X off of that pod. Now,
what do you suppose is going to happen
when I do that? Let's see and find
out. Interesting. This is the pod where
I removed the label. And look what the
deployment did. It didn't go out and
look for the pod that lost the label.
That deployment assumed, oh, that pod's
gone. I'm going to go ahead and create a
brand new one to replace it. Because the
rule is always maintain this number. No
more, no less.
Now, what do you suppose is going to
happen if I were to put that label back
on top of that exact same
pot? Well, like I said, it's two
replicas, no more and no less. And
uh it wound up keeping the original pod,
which is nice. But try as you might, if
you were to delete these pods, they're
just going to keep coming back. Uh they
are absolutely bulletproof. The only way
to actually get rid of all of the pods
that are inside of a deployment is to
either delete the deployment itself or
scale the number of pods down to zero.
So soon as I deleted the deployment, you
notice that it's gone. Now, there's one
last thing that I want to show you here
just before we start doing some death by
PowerPoint is I'm going to go ahead and
I'm going to create this deployment one
more time.
What is technically inaccurate that
everybody says is that deployments make
pods. That's not right. The pods that
are being created by this deployment are
actually being created by what's known
as a replica set. Replica sets are an
much older type of Kubernetes resource
than deployments. They've been around
since the very beginning. The problem
with replica sets was is that trying to
swap them out inside of production was
getting to be a little bit too much of a
headache. But to prove to you that this
is the case, let me show you something
here. If I were to show uh what pods we
have, notice that the replica set is
named after the deployment and it has
its own unique little string.
These pods here are actually being named
after the replica set. And you see how
they're sharing the same value. So, it's
kind of interesting and it's just a way
that you can see which pods are being
made by what replica set at a glance.
All right, but let's talk a little bit
more about some of the theory behind
using deployments. All right. So, as
you've already seen, deployments create
replica sets, and replica sets are what
create pods. And where those pods go on
which node inside of your cluster,
unless you are setting otherwise, the
scheduler is what's going to make that
decision. As long as the number of
replicas that the replica set is
supposed to make exist, it's happy to
let them live and let live wherever they
may be.
Now, why even use deployments if replica
sets are doing all the work? Ah, now
here's the rub. Deployments can do
everything replica sets can do because
deployments after all make replica sets.
But what they can also do is that they
can version control. And this is what I
was saying earlier about how replica
sets weren't working so great inside of
production. You can roll out and roll
back changes that are being made to your
pods. And you can do that in a way that
there is zero downtime for your clients.
They'll never even notice that the pods
got swapped out. And unlike other types
of objects where you make changes to the
manifest, if you try to push those
changes against a running resource,
you'll get errors a lot of the time. But
deployments, they expect change. They
are designed to make change. And I'll
show you how that works in just a sec.
All right. So, here's what winds up
happening. You have a deployment that
has that made a replica set that made a
whole bunch of pods, but you decide that
you want to make a fundamental change to
how those pods are created. What winds
up happening is that the deployment
doesn't fix this replica set. No, no,
no. It goes ahead and creates a new
replica set, a second one. And as part
of this rolling update process, which is
the default, you'd have to like go an
extra step to make this not be the case.
The way that it works is that it will
surge ahead one pod. So now we have four
pods instead of uh three. And then it
will delete one of the old ones. Notice
at no time do we have less than the
normal number of pods, three. Then it
surges ahead. It adds one new pod. Then
it removes one of the old pots. Then it
adds that third and final pod. And then
it removes that last pot. So this is how
deployments are able to make these
changes without actually any downtime.
Sure, there might be a moment where
you're kind of split between two
different versions of a deployment.
There's other ways to get around that,
but if you're trying to roll out simple
changes, deployments are designed to do
that.
Now, what's also super neat is that you
can roll back those changes. Watch this.
If I wanted to go back from this version
back to this version, all we have to do
is have the deployment go back to using
this replica set. So, it's almost like
this goes back in reverse. One of these
pods gets removed over there. new pod
gets added over there, gets added there,
gets added there, gets added there, gets
added there, until eventually we're back
to three pods here, and no pods over
there. So, it's a really neat little
system, and it's something you'll be
using to create the majority of your
pods in Kubernetes. Now, let's
demonstrate that a little bit. I'm going
to go ahead and I'm going to create the
manifest that you see over on the left
hand side of my screen. I am making 10
pots using this manifest. And you'll see
what it did is that immediately it
created a replica set. So what you're
seeing here is the first and only
replica set that this deployment has
made so far. Now suppose that I'm making
a change. I want each of those pods, all
10 of them, to not have one container
inside of them, but two.
And let's just say that oh I don't know
we want to put like a reddus image
inside of it. It doesn't really matter
what the image is but the point is you
cannot add new containers to pods that
are already running. So this will be a
good demo. Now I want you to watch very
carefully on what happens when I hit
enter here. You're going to see a second
replica set appear. you're going to see
the number of available pods for that
replica set go up and the number of pods
for this replica set will go down
because that's that rolling update that
I was telling you about earlier. So
there it goes. One is increasing, one is
decreasing, effortlessly flowing from
one to the next. Boom. Done. So, all 10
of those pods have been recreated, and
now all of those pods have the two uh
containers inside of them, as you can
see right here. But here's what's super
sexy about deployments is that you can
not only roll out changes, you can roll
back changes. So what I'm going to do is
I'm going to use a whole new uh command
here cube control rollout history of our
deployment called demo
deployment. This history keeps track of
how many revisions has this gone
through. And there's lots of cool things
you can do with this command that we'll
talk about more in the full course, but
I do want to show you just this one. If
I were to do a cube control roll out
history
undo, what that will do is that it will
take my current revision. I'm in the
second revision right now. And it will
roll it back to the previous
revision. That's possible because all
we're going to do is we're going to go
from 10 down there to 10 up here. So, as
soon as I run that command, oops, it's
cube control roll out
undo on the deployment demo deploy.
There we go. You can see that uh the
numbers are switching and now it's
rolling back one at a time just like it
did the first time when we rolled it
out. Next, we're going to talk about
storage. Ooh, fun. Storage, Chad said
sarcastically. Storage is complicated.
Uh, not the least of which is because
every company, every team out there
wants to use storage differently inside
of their cluster, like where the storage
is located, what kind of storage it is.
Uh, it's just a big kurfuffle. And
Kubernetes has gone through a lot of
changes over the years and how it
handles this. But the good news is is
that no matter what type of storage you
may use, whether it's AWS, as I'm just
using as an example here, or something
else, it's going to follow this exact
same formula. So suppose that we uh need
to put storage uh for our containers to
access. Now, of course, putting storage
inside of the container itself is no
good because containers they die all the
time and containers are stateless and
containers are supposed to be small. So,
we're not putting gigs of data inside of
containers after all. They need to be
stored remotely like in the cloud or on
a disk or something like that. So, what
we're going to be doing here is that we
need to basically chart a path between
the container inside of our pod and our
storage, which might be in the cloud or
on a disk or
wherever. Here's the process. First
thing that you need to do is that you
need to teach your cluster how to handle
the storage that you want to use.
Kubernetes is storage agnostic, which
means it's team AWS, it's team Azure,
it's team whatever you want, baby, as
long as you teach it what it is that you
need it needs to know. That's done
through creating something called a
storage class.
Once you have a storage class created
and now that DNA is inside of your
cluster, you are then able to start
allocating, call them chunks of storage
space that can be set aside and used
specifically for your pods and their
containers. So let's say that out of my
cloud here there's like a 3 gigabyte
chunk that I want to uh access that is
saved inside of something called a
persistent volume. So persistent volumes
are what teaches your cluster on how to
create certain types of storage and
handle it. Persistent volumes are what
represent that storage itself. And the
persistent volume AWS that you're seeing
here will be made uh entirely
differently if I was using Azure or
something. It makes training very
difficult because you know the
parameters are so different from vendor
to vendor. All right. So that must be it
right. No that's not it. All right.
Everything in Kubernetes is very
decoupled. All right. The persistent
volume represents the storage. What we
need in next is something that
represents access and that is called a
persistent volume claim. So I suppose
you could visualize this as the
persistent volume claim is the key and
the persistent volume is the locker. All
right, these two are wedded together and
it is a monogous relationship. There is
one persistent volume claim that binds
to one persistent volume. So there won't
be multiple persistent volume claims
mount mounting up to the same persistent
volume. Doesn't work that way. But it is
that persistent volume claim that gets
mounted as a volume to the actual pod
itself. And if you watch the section on
config maps and secrets when we already
walked through how volumes are added,
then it's a very similar process. All
right, you add the volume to the pod.
You then add that volume attached to the
pod mounted to a directory inside of the
container. And there you go. We have
created a full flow of storage that
anything that gets saved inside of this
directory by the pods
container. Let's work it back here. Oh,
the mount path connected to the volume.
The volume represents the persistent
volume claim. The persistent volume
claim is connected to the persistent
volume which is abstracted a space
that's taken from the storage space. The
storage space is uh recognized by
Kubernetes because you taught it through
a storage class and that's how you store
your
stuff. God. All
right. Now it should be pointed out like
much like when we were talking about
config maps is that you can mount mult
you can mount a config map to multiple
pods you can mount storage to multiple
containers because after all if both of
these pods are say part of the same
deployment they are identical to each
other airgo they should have access to
the same storage then attaching them to
this persistent volume claim is uh
perfectly doable and very easily
done. Now, in the demo that I'm about to
do, we are going to create a persistent
volume, a persistent volume claim, a pod
that mounts it, and we're going to see
data persist when we do it. All right,
that being said, this is going to be a
very low tech demonstration, although
everything in it is absolutely
fundamental, no matter what type of
storage you might use. But we're not
going to play favorites between
Microsoft and you know all that stuff
like uh it is what it is. So what we're
going to do is that we are going to use
an extremely simple storage class called
the manual storage class. What's that
mean? It means that we are just going to
manually choose a node. Node one, node
two, I don't know. We're gonna pick a
node and we are going to take a chunk of
storage space from it and use that as
our persistent volume. So that three
gigs that's being represented by this
persistent volume is going to be taken
from one of our nodes. Perfectly valid
way to do it if a little primitive.
We're then going to create a persistent
volume claim that maps to it. Once we've
done that, we're going to actually see
them bind together. We're going to take
the persistent volume claim. We are
going to make sure that we write a
manifest that mounts it. Now, what we're
going to do when we make this pod is
that we are going to intentionally
create it on top of node one. So, you're
also going to see how you can force pods
to go onto certain nodes. All right.
What's going to wind up happening is
that because this pod goes on node one,
this persistent volume will take its
storage from node one as well. And
what's going to happen is that we're
going to make a file over here inside of
our mount path data. And what we're
going to see is that that file is
actually going to be physically located
on node one. So if you work all the way
back, we should find index.html there.
All right, let's go to the command line
and let's try all this out. Okay, so
we've got three manifests that we need
to make here. And we're going to put
them all inside of the same document
because why not?
And first thing we're making is a
persistent volume. And at first it's not
so crazy. It's not super long. But we do
see some new things here under spec.
Storage class name is where you select.
All right. What storage class am I
using? Like in order to like build this
persistent volume. You need to have
created the storage class in advance of
having done this. Most storage classes
you can just find the manifests for them
like with whatever vendor it is that
you're using. So that's good news.
Capacity is how large is the persistent
volume going to be. And because we are
using just a local storage here manual
host path means where on the node is
going to be the directory where we're
taking the three gigs of storage from.
So in other words, anything that gets
saved to this persistent volume, we
should find on the node inside of that
directory. Now, access modes, uh, there
obviously are several different things
that you can set there, but read write
once means that the volume can be
mounted as read write by a single node
at a time, which means that just one
node can be writing to it at a time,
right? It's the most common type of
access for like a real basic type of
storage like
this. All right. Now, if I want to add
uh something else inside of the same
manifest, I can do that. YAML separates
one document from the other by using
those three dashes that you see there.
What I'm now going to do is I'm going to
add my persistent volume claim.
The only thing that's needed for this
persistent volume claim to find that
persistent volume is that they have the
same storage class. There are other ways
to guarantee that they connect, but
that's not necessary in what we're doing
right here. It's got the same access
mode. We're going to use up all of the
storage that that persistent volume has
uh available to it. And that's all that
it's going to take. Now, of course,
there are far more complicated
persistent volumes, persistent volume
claims that you can make, and we explore
those more inside of our full course,
but again, we're keeping it super simple
for this fundamentals course that we're
doing right here. All right, so last
thing that we need to do is that we need
to create a pod. And what we need to do
is we need to walk through all that
volume mounting stuff again, right? So,
remember what's the first thing that you
need to do? You first need to mount the
object as a volume. So under volumes,
we're saying that hey, I want the
persistent volume claim called enginex
PVC. Remember that is the name of our
persistent volume claim up here. I want
that mounted to that pod as a volume.
Let's refer to the volume as EngineXPV
storage. All right. So we now have the
volume added to the pod. We now need to
add the volume to the
container. So in my container here, I'm
going to add volume mounts. Again, the
name of the volume matches what's down
here. And as I've done with config maps
in the past, I'm going to pick a
directory inside of the container where
I want that uh persistent volume claim
to be accessed. So if you go to
slashdata you are going to persistent
volume claim and if you're going to
persistent volume claim you're going to
the persistent volume. If you're going
to the persistent volume you are going
to the node. Right? So anything that we
put in this directory is going to get
written to the node. Now, speaking of
the node, there's one last thing that uh
we need to do here for this
demonstration is we're going to use the
node selector
uh parameter. There are several ways to
force pods to go onto certain uh nodes
in your cluster. And really, you should
only be doing this when you have to,
right? There's some circumstances we can
talk about later, but basically, hey,
only go on top of those nodes where the
host name is node one. Obviously, this
is going to put this on top of node one.
So, let me get all my ducks in a row
here real
quick. Yeah, I'm just going to um nudge
the uh node selector over a little bit
because I definitely did not uh indent
that properly. Whoops. Yeah, it's got to
be lined up like under a spec like with
the C in containers. Oopsy
daisy. All right. So, the moment that we
created that, take a look at what we saw
appear that we I know it's kind of
wrapped around my screen and that makes
it difficult to see, but our persistent
volume claim is bound and that has been
bound to our persistent volume
uh excuse me, the persistent volume has
been bound to that persistent volume
claim. All right. And everything's
bearing out exactly as we said that it
would. What's also interesting is is
that when I said in my persistent volume
claim that I wanted the capacity to be
one gig, it's two. Why' it go to two?
Because the persistent volume was two.
And it's like, what am I supposed to do
with this extra gig? Just waste it? Nah.
So, it's kind of interesting that it
automatically scaled that up. All right.
So, now that that's done, here's what
we're going to do next. We're going to
cube control exec inside of that pod and
we're going to take a peek inside of
that data
directory. First of all, the fact that
there's a data directory at all means
that our volume mount definitely did
work. And what I'm going to do is I'm
going to echo help. I'm trapped in a
file and I can't get out. I'm going to
put that inside of a file called
proof.txt.
Now, let's hop on out of
that. If that were the case, and if this
did persist, there's a couple of things
that we need to try out first. First of
all, I'm going to kill all these pods
because I had a deployment running at
some point. All right, that uh pod that
had the storage attached is now dead.
I'm going to rebuild that pod again.
I'm going to hop inside of that pod
again and inside of the data directory
I'm going to see is there a proof.txt
file. Right. Yes, there is. So that
right there is proof that this is
persisting. We are using storage. What
I'm also going to show you is that that
pod that I made is going to uh be on top
of node
one because we used we entered that
inside of the selector, right? Node one.
Let's SSH over into node one really
quick. And let me get this manifest up
there at the top so I can prove
something to you here real quick. All
right.
SSH node
one and let's go inside of the mount
data directory. Remember how we said
that that was the host path inside of
our persistent volume? Well, when I look
inside of this directory, lo and behold,
there's
proof.txt. And when I got that out,
help. I'm trapped in a file and I can't
get out. Just goes to show that the data
is persistent, that it is in a location
other than the container itself. And
while this is a very primitive form of
storage, no matter what type of storage
you use, it's all going to come down to
this. Storage classes, persistent
volumes, and persistent volume claims.
Okay, the time has come for us to start
charting a course into the murky waters
of networking inside of Kubernetes. And
I promise we're getting there. But
showing rather than telling is always my
style. What I'm going to do here is I'm
going to create a deployment. It's going
to be using Engine X. I'm specifying
that the port is port 80. And I do need
to put the two dashes in front of that
there because that's something that's
going to be important for later. Uh I
also want there to be three pods made by
this deployment. And there you go. Nice
quick and dirty
deployment. Now what I'm going to do
next is that I am going to create a
service
exposing this deployment. Now what is a
service thing is is that in Kubernetes
for any uh pod to be communicated with
what it basically needs is a great big
neon sign like you'd see flashing inside
of Las Vegas basically saying here it is
here it is here's the pod that you're
looking
for. Why is that necessary? Well, let me
show you something interesting. If I do
a uh cube control get pods and let's get
a few uh
extra uh columns of information out
there. You can see that each and every
one of these pods has its own unique IP
address.
Right now, if I were to delete one of
those pods, let's just go ahead and
delete the very first one that you see
there.
Now that's
247.34. It's on node two. What guarantee
do you suppose there is that that pod
when it gets rebuilt and it will will
have that exact same IP address or even
that'll be on that same node
again. Like practically none. All right.
And that's an entirely different IP
address. It's still on node two because
theuler figured, oh, there's nothing on
node two. But point is that IP addresses
they change and as deployments like get
scaled up and down and as pods get
deleted and so on and so forth. IP
addresses are a constantly moving
target. All right. So this is kind of
the nightmare we find ourselves in with
Kubernetes. Fortunately, we got a really
cool, really clever solution
here. Now I'm going to do this using a
cube control command. Although we
certainly could write a manifest to do
this. I'm going to expose the deployment
called demo
deploy. And as a result of that command,
what just got created was a new type of
object called a
service. There are three different kinds
of services which we're going to talk
about a little bit later, but the one
that we just made and is most common is
known as a cluster IP service.
And notice that this service has its own
IP
address. All right. Now, why is that
relevant? I'll show you in just a
second. Now, let's get all those pods uh
up and visible one more time. Again, get
pods output wide. And let's open up
another pane here. do a watch
uh cube control describe our service
called uh demo
deploy. Now what you're seeing inside of
this description is uh well a couple of
things but for one I can see the IP
address 172.16.3.105 105 that's one but
there are one two three other IP
addresses here where do you suppose
those are coming from you might have
already guessed but those are the IP
addresses of all these pods that you see
over here right each and every one of
them is being matched up and what's
super cool about services is is watch
what happens when I scale the deployment
demo deploy from three replicas
down to just
one. Two of those pods get deleted and
look what happens to the service
automatically. It just tracks the IP
address of the one remaining pod. And if
I scale that up to like 10, and the next
thing you know, bip one, two, three,
plus seven more, 10 IP addresses. So, as
chaotic as pods getting created and
destroyed are, here's what's really
nice. Between all those changing IP
addresses, do you see the IP address
that did not change, not even once that
whole
time? It's the IP address of the
service. So, think of it this way. If
the service always knows where the IP
address of the pod is and pod IP
addresses change all the time, if you
know the IP address of the service,
you're gold because the service is what
will point you in the right direction.
So that's the method behind the madness
and that's how services work. We're
going to talk more about those in
greater detail, but first we need to set
some ground rules. All right, so what do
I mean by that? Well, now that that
deployment has been exposed by a
service, it means that other pods inside
of your cluster can actually talk to
those uh pods. So to do that, I'm going
to make this pod here. It's going to do
all my talking for me. This uh pod
called client is running by. And by is
nice because it lets you execute
commands like curl. And uh we can see if
we can use it to get network
connectivity. So, I'm going to go ahead
and I'm going to make that pod client.
I'm going to cube control exec inside of
that
pod. And I do have the curl command uh
inside of this. Never mind. I'm not
going to use curl. I'm going to use
wget. And what I'm going to do is that I
am going
to do
this inside of my container. I'm going
to type wget then the name of the
service demo
deploy. Now
remember the service is what is pointing
to the pods. The pods and my deployment
are all running enginex
images. So when I say I want to download
like whatever is at that service at that
pod look what wound up happening. It
downloaded
index.html. What's that? It's the
welcome to engineext page. How cool.
We've just had podto pod
communication. We downloaded the welcome
page. And right now, every pod inside of
our cluster is able to do that. They can
access and talk to and work with the
pods inside that deployment. It's peace
and love, man. Everybody loves
everybody,
man. That's the security nightmare.
So, we need to control this. While yes,
pods do need to communicate, we also
need to set rules about which pods are
allowed to talk to which pods. And to do
that, we're going to create a new type
of object called a network
policy. And I'm not going to lie,
network policies from all of the
hundreds of students that I've worked
with in Kubernetes, uh, is just the most
nightmare of a manifest you'll ever see.
Look at this
thing. Granted, not all network policies
are this big and ugly, but if I can
teach you how this network policy works,
then there's no network policy out there
that's going to phase you. All right,
ready? Let's get down to it. So, network
policies, much like resource quotas and
limit ranges and other things, are
assigned to name spaces. So you attach
the network policy and what that means
is is that this network policy is going
to affect just those pods that are
inside of this specific namespace. So
that's an important thing to point out
right off the bat. You need to target
the namespace of the pods you wish to
control. Right? So that's step number
one.
Step number two, when we crack open the
spec. Oh boy. All
right. Basically, network policy if you
boil it all down is really simple. It's
all about controlling ingress and
egress, which is to say traffic that is
coming in and egress, which is traffic
that is going out. You can configure
network policies to uh control both or
just one or the other. I always kind of
visualize a network policy as like a
helicopter parent, you know, somebody
who's like right on top of their kid
like all the time. Like I don't want you
talking to that Jimmy down the street.
No, he's not good people. All right?
Like I want you to only talk to that boy
Melvin next door. Oh, he's a good kid.
That's exactly how a network policy
works. All right. So, policy types is
where you list what things is this
network policy going to control.
Ingress, egress, both, just the one. You
get it? Pod selector is where we
basically are saying what pods are we
controlling using this network policy.
So if the network policy is the
helicopter parent, then who is the kid
who's getting
parented? And what we're doing here is
we're using match labels just like we
did with deployments. Like I said,
labels are so important in Kubernetes.
And basically the way this works is is
that if you are in the default namespace
and if you have the label RO DB, you are
about to have your traffic coming in and
coming out
controlled and certain criteria has to
be met. All right, so let's go on down
to the bottom
part here. Here is where we're going to
be setting up what are the rules that
have to be followed in order for traffic
to actually work. So for ingress here,
we're making our first list of rules.
We're saying that traffic has to come
from one of the following sources. Now,
you don't have to use all of these. In
fact, most folks won't. But again, this
is the longest and dirtiest example that
I could find. So, we'll just go ahead
and use that IP block allows us to
specify a cider range of IP addresses
like it's got to be that pod in this
range otherwise we're not going to allow
that pod to send ingress except and you
can advertise exceptions if it's in like
this range or this particular one right
here that it's going to be uh not
allowed. Pods can talk to each other
across namespaces which is interesting.
So even if pods are in different
namespaces if one is uh you know exposed
by a service it's not safe other pods
and other namespaces can access it. So
namespace
selector is where we can say that hey
pods in the default namespace that have
the label ro db you are only allowed to
receive traffic from pods that are in
this IP address range or pods that are
from any nameace that has the label
project my
project. So again, this is uh going a
label that's on the namespace itself.
You can put labels on all kinds of
different things. So in other words,
must be from this nameace or must be
from this IP
range or and this is the most common way
honestly that we see these getting
established pod
selector from specific pods like it must
be from pod with this label roll front
end. So to go back through all that one
more time, listen up. All pods in the
default namespace that have the label RO
DB, the following uh changes are about
to go into effect. You may only receive
incoming traffic from pods in this IP
range or pods from that nameace or pods
that have this particular role.
Make sure that you're being very careful
with the rules of uh how network policy
works because these are all or
situations and you got to make sure
you're really spelling out very
particularly in a test environment that
that's exactly what you mean and what
you need. Uh what you can also do for
ingress is that for ports you can
specify all right pods that are being
targeted by my helicopter parenting. You
can only receive traffic into port
6379. You could also list other ports if
you want. Unfortunately, egress is very
much the exact same thing. It uses very
much the same language except now we're
saying all right pods in default with
the label RO DB. You are only allowed to
send traffic to pods inside of that IP
address range. And when you do send it,
you're only allowed to send it to their
port 5978.
So, you can mix and match all of these
in either section or you can choose to
not include them at all, which is
perfectly fine. All right, but make sure
that you're being very precise with uh
the rules you're putting in your network
policy and test
test. So, very quickly before we move
on, let's demonstrate actual network
policies in practice. Now, there are no
network policies in uh my system at all
at the moment. I can uh inside of my
client pod send a request to another
pod, an enginex pod. And right there you
can see I downloaded that
index.html file. But what I'm now going
to do is that I'm going to apply this
network policy that you see here. And
what you're seeing, this is what's
called a default deny network policy.
What's happening here is is that all
pods in the default
namespace are about to be told where
they are allowed to receive traffic from
and where they are allowed to receive
traffic to. Pod selector open close
curly braces means all pods. So we're
selecting all the pods in the default
name space. Now looking at that network
policy, where are the rules that say
what we are allowed to do? Because
remember a network policy, if you aren't
doing what the policy says is permitted,
it's not permitted at
all. Oh shoot, we never actually gave
any rules to like what uh exceptions
there were. Which means that this is why
this is a default deny. Watch when I run
this wget command
again. It's hanging. It's not going to
connect. So, the network policy is kind
of slapping our hands here, so to speak.
And, uh, that's no good. We need to
change that up a little bit. Now, uh, if
we go back and we take a look at the
manifest for my pod that is trying to
access Engine X, it's got the label run
client on top of it.
Basically, if this is what I want to do,
if I want my EngineX pods to be able to
accept traffic from pods that have the
label app engine X, then here's what I
would need to do. I would first need to
see what are the labels that are on my
uh deployment pods. Looks like they've
all got uh app demo deploy as their
label. So, let's go over here and for
pod selector, we're going to change
things up a little bit. Match labels app
demo deploy. So now this network policy
is no longer applying to all of the pods
inside of the default namespace, just
those deployment pods. And I'm not too
worried about egress. I'm worried about
ingress traffic going into those enginex
pods. And what I'm now going to do down
here below is, and I'm just going to
paste this in is that we are going to uh
specify where is ingress allowed to come
from. ingress to my EngineX deployment
pods can only come from pods that have
the label run client on
them. So having made those changes and
running cube control apply to my network
policy. So the policy has been updated.
My uh client pod using busy box is still
up here and running. I'm going to run
wget one more time and see if it works.
So what we've successfully done is that
we've been able to configure our network
policy to allow this specific
interaction. Although literally any
other interaction that these uh
deployment pods are trying to make would
be prohibited. All right, we got a
little death by PowerPoint coming your
way here, but hopefully it's going to
clear up a few things. Now, we had made
a service prior by using the cube
control expose command. This is what a
service manifest looks like. It's not
super uh terribly uh difficult. But
again, notice that uh we're using
selector just like we did with
deployments, just like we were doing
with um network policies to say which uh
pods are being affected. So our selector
is choosing this pod. Oh, excuse me. Our
selector is choosing this pod right
here. It's got that label. Now the
question is is what are the meanings of
these port numbers that you see right
here.
Well, the thing is is that target port
refers to the port that is on the
target. And since we are using engine X
inside of this pod, remember X's
container port is 80. That's written in
stone. That's not something that you can
change. Port. This value right here is
actually the port on the service itself.
And what this is doing is that it is
mapping a direct relationship to say
that hey if you go to this service at
this IP
address and you go to that port at that
IP address 3 423 it'll take you to this
port to that EngineX container allowing
you to access the
application. Now the reason why that
exists is is let's expand this a little
bit.
Whoop. It is possible for pods to have
more than one container inside of them.
And if a service is going to redirect
traffic to that pod, well, how am I
supposed to be able to access the
specific container that I want? Well,
the same rule here still applies. If you
go to this service and you access it
through that port, it is going to take
you to port 80 which is going to connect
you to the engine X
container. But look what we can also do
is that we can add a whole other port
protocol here that if you go to say port
4444 that'll take you to port 8888 which
is running some other application. So
services can be configured to go to
different ports even if they are
entirely different containers inside of
the same pods that they are exposing. So
that's the difference between port
target port and just wait because it's
ports of plenty over here. We're going
to be talking about node
ports. All right. In this animation, we
are going to start talking about podto
pod communication and services in a
visual way so that you can see how these
tools work and interact, which hopefully
is going to help you understand that
Kubernetes does a lot of networking
stuff under the hood. It's really nice
to not have to worry about these things
on a day-to-day basis, but you really do
need to understand this stuff in my
opinion. So in the story that I'm
telling you, super simple cluster, one
node, there are two pods. They're on the
same node as each other. And pod number
one there is all like, "Oh, gee whiz,
I'd really like to talk to pod number
three." So how does that work? We know
from what we've learned earlier that pod
number three needs to be exposed by a
service. Now let's say that that service
is already created. But the question is
is how is that service located? How is
it accessed? So on and so forth. Here is
where the great and mighty cube proxy is
going to come into play. And cube proxy
is a lot like
cublet. Kubernetes loves putting the
word cube inside of everything. And
there is a cube proxy located on every
node inside of your cluster. And what
cube proxy has access to is the IP table
of every single node inside of your
cluster. Which means that the cube proxy
is perfectly able to look and see ah
there's a service here called pod 3. The
IP address uh that that service is
exposing is
10.1.2.1. That's the IP address of the
pod. So in this case, the cube proxy's
job is very easy. It checks the service.
It sees that that service is pointing to
just one pod here. And as a
result, our pod is given the IP address
and then routing is able to take place.
Once the IP address of the pod is
located, it's game over. All right,
that's the end goal here. But remember
that the headache that we face with
Kubernetes is that we have dozens if not
hundreds of pods with constantly
changing IP addresses. So we need some
method on top of this madness. Now let's
scale it out a little bit and let's get
a slightly more difficult uh scenario.
Let's say once again we've got a pod
that really wants to talk to one of
those pods inside of the zombie
deployment. We just named it
zombie because all of these pods are
identical. They're all replicas, right?
It doesn't matter which pod this pod
talks to. Okay, so that's an interesting
uh conundrum because once again, we
reach out to great and mighty Cube Proxy
for uh connection advice. So, what Cube
Proxy is going to do is that it's going
to check its service table. It's going
to find one called zombie and it's going
to see that there are three IP addresses
to choose from. The Q proxy is
responsible for setting up the rules on
or rather obeying the rules of which IP
address gets selected.
And what will wind up happening is that
it will use a roundroin by default
approach that hey if the last time
somebody came knocking on my door asking
for a zombie pod and I sent them to
1.3.1 this time I'm going to send them
to
1.3.2. So it's cube proxy that's
ultimately making the decision here
which one of these three pods is going
to be the one that winds up talking to
busy box. And what also happens as like
a mwah part of that process is that
qroxy will also make sure that that pod
is healthy before a decision gets made.
So if this con pod is still in container
creating or it's erroring out then that
pod won't get chosen. It'll instead hop
down to the next one and then it will
choose that pod instead. So in this
story we'll say hey I'm going to go with
node two. All right that's just how the
cookie crumbles in this story.
And now we're going to take it even
further
back. Once again, let's say that we've
got a deployment that's making pods. The
deployment's making three identical
pods. Two of those pods happen to be on
node two and one of those pods happens
to be on node three. That's just the way
that it works out.
And now that we're looking at a
multi-node cluster, everything that I
was telling you about cube proxy applies
to all of the nodes. Now, take a look at
the table that I've got in each one of
those nodes that you see here. What do
you notice about
it? They're all the same, right? So, it
doesn't matter where you go. any cube
proxy in any node whether you have a
cluster of one node or 50 nodes they're
all going to have access to the same
routing information. So this uh begs the
question how is one going to connect to
one of those pods? Well before I move on
to the next point let's do a little uh
exercise here real quick. Suppose that I
have a pod down here on node three. This
is using a busy box image. And let's say
that it needs to talk to one of the
zombie pods. And it says, "Oh, great and
mighty Cube proxy. Please pick a pod for
me." Cube Proxy goes and it looks at all
these IP
addresses. Is it a guarantee that
Cuberoxy is going to choose
10.1.2.1? No, not at all. That is not
important. it can't be important. Cube
Proxy will use roundroin to determine
what the next pod is going to be chosen.
So, my pod that I drew right here might
wind up talking to a pod over on top of
this other node. And that's okay because
think of it, if that pod had been
created over here on top of node number
one, and I said, "Hey, I needed to talk
to one of those zombie pods." I'm gonna
have to wind up talking to a pod on a
different node anyway.
So because things are always so chaotic,
we can't be taking the time to think,
oh, is this pod in the same node as this
other pod? That doesn't
matter. All right. Now, everything that
we've just been describing, podto pod
communication, has all been a specific
type of service known as a cluster IP
service. And there are three types of
services. There's the cluster IP
service, there's a node port service,
and there is a load balancer service.
And each of these services build on the
one that came before them. So if we have
an idea of how cluster IP services work,
let's take a step up now to a node port
service. Now, uh what you'll see here is
that our tables have changed somewhat.
are zombie services are no longer
cluster IP services they are node port
services which means they have a node
port this will always be a number
between 30,000 and 32,000 something
something something right point is node
ports are always very
recognizable all right nodeport services
are uh the most primitive type of
service that actually allows external
access into the cluster
without using cube
control. Check this out. If you have a
client who has the IP addresses of one
of your nodes and has the node port of
one of your
services, that client is able to access
whatever pod is being pointed to. So,
let's walk that
through. If I were to send a curl to
192.168.0.12,
0.12 that
is this node right
here. When we reach that node, we are
accessing it via port
31234, which is the node port that's
attached to our zombie
service. At which point, guess what? The
cube proxy says, "Ah, I see you're
trying to access zombie." And then the
exact same behavior from before occurs.
Qroxy is going to use round robin to
determine which one of these pods should
we go to next. Is it guaranteed going to
be this pod? No, we've already said
that. It's going to use round robin to
choose. So if it turns out
10.1.3.2 is the IP address that gets
chosen. Even though we sent a curl
request to node 3, we wind up accessing
a pod on node two, which is perfectly
normal. And if that seems strange to
you, well, imagine if we had a 50 node
cluster and there's one pod on those 50.
You have a one in 50 chance of guessing
the correct node. That couldn't possibly
work. So that's how node balancers work.
Uh, excuse me, that's how node ports
work in a nutshell. and it's a a method
of how you can access your pods
ultimately from an external connection.
Now the third type of service that we're
going to talk about are load
balancers and load balancers are more
sophisticated. Load balancers still use
node ports as you can see
here. But a load balancer requires some
sort of external machine of to your
cluster with an outwardfacing IP address
to accept incoming traffic. If your
Kubernetes cluster is in the cloud, ah
they be they those folks Azure and uh
Amazon, they love to take your money and
they'll spin up a load balancer for you.
It's coming from a place of jealousy
because like we all do all our work on
bare metal. But point is is that you do
need to provision that. Uh Kubernetes
does not come with load balancers. It's
happy to work with load balancers that
you will provide it but that's not
something that is
included. But once you have a load
balancer, what's nice about this is is
that your client can now go to that load
balancer instead of going straight to
one of your nodes inside of the cluster.
And what the load balancer will do is
that it will say, "All right, enough of
this roundroin stuff, which is not true
load balancing. I'm going to make a uh
educated decision about which pod is
going to wind up getting selected." And
thanks to uh the fact that load
balancers also use node ports, it can
choose whichever node it wants. It can
access the IP table through the node
port. It can choose the IP address of
the pod that it wants and can ultimately
chart uh routing that way. All right,
it's pictures worth a thousand words.
Let's get down to the command line and
let's actually make some services and
let's see how node ports work. So, I've
created this pod here. And before I
start setting up any services at all,
I'm going to go ahead and open up a port
forward. And let's just do port
2224. And that is going to port 80. And
so long as that port forward is open, I
can curl localhost.
And uh the way that this is set up is
that inside of this pod there is a
endpoint which is uh called
slashstatic and that's just a little
repository that has a file in it called
engineext.txt. Inside of that little txt
file says you done did a
networking. So notice I needed a port
forward in order for this to work. like
I needed cube control access in order to
access what was going on inside of that
container. All right, but we're going to
change that because what we're going to
do next is that we are going to create a
uh we are going to expose excuse me
rather that uh pod with a node port type
service. So, we're going to do cubec
control exposed pod engine x configured.
And what I need to explicitly state here
is that our type is node port. By
default, it's going to be cluster IP.
Otherwise, so I'm going to go ahead and
expose that pod that created the
service. And if I were to describe the
service that I just created for EngineX
uh configured, it's pretty much the same
as what we'd seen before. But notice
that the type says node
port and that there is also now a field
node port
30337 that was assigned automatically.
So that number right there
30337 is something that uh we need to
remember.
Now what I'm going to do is
this. Let's get that curl command back
in
here. What I'm going to do is that I'm
not going to through my local hosts uh
cube control connection. I'm instead
going to go to one of my nodes. So let's
do it this way. cube control get nodes
outputwide. The IP address of my first
node is
10.14.24.245. Let's do this. I'm going
to curl. That's node number one. I'm
going to go to that node port
30337. That should access my
uh service which should access the pod.
Which means that if I throw
slashstatic.txt txt onto the end of it.
You done did a networking. Super cool.
This is just a straight curl command.
I'm not using cube control or any other
kind of special permissions. I just had
the IP address of the node and the node
port. Now remember what I was telling
you earlier that it does not matter what
node the pod is on. As long as you are
using the IP address of one of those
nodes, uh, it'll work because cube proxy
is everywhere. So to prove it, I'm going
to grab the IP address of my second node
right here. And let's run this
again. This is the IP address for my
second node. Same node port, same
everything else. still works, which just
again is just kind of the proof that
node ports are accessible and can be
used to track pods no matter where you
are in the cluster. And if you are
planning on taking the CKAD or the CKA
exam, it's pretty much a guarantee that
there will be some node port service
related question on that exam. And there
you have it. That's our crash course in
Kubernetes fundamentals. But there is
still so much more to learn. Though
we've covered everything in this course
from YAML all the way up to networking,
there are still many more things that
need to be learned in order for you to
especially pass the CKA or the CKD exam.
That's why I recommend that if you truly
wish to master Kubernetes, get your
hands dirty, and do what you need to do
to succeed, check out Alta 3 Academy.
All this content and way more is waiting
for you, including a work environment,
the same environment that I was using in
this demo. An AI instructor that will
answer any question, no matter how
simple or complicated, plus full mock
exams for the CKA and the CKAD, so you
can test your skills and make sure that
you are really learning and prepared to
get out there and take Kubernetes by the
horns. So, click that link down in the
description and take the next step
towards becoming a true Kubernetes
expert. I hope to see you there. Make
sure that you like and subscribe and
I'll see you next time.